<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Certaine homilies of m. Ioan Calvine conteining profitable and necessarie, admonitio[n] for this time, with an apologie of Robert Horn.</title>
            <title>Quatre sermons. English. Selections</title>
            <author>Calvin, Jean, 1509-1564.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1553</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 163 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 60 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A17636</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 4392</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S107180</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99842882</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99842882</idno>
            <idno type="VID">7578</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A17636)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 7578)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 488:07)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Certaine homilies of m. Ioan Calvine conteining profitable and necessarie, admonitio[n] for this time, with an apologie of Robert Horn.</title>
                  <title>Quatre sermons. English. Selections</title>
                  <author>Calvin, Jean, 1509-1564.</author>
                  <author>Horne, Robert, 1519?-1580.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[122] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Before the castle of .s. Angel, at the signe of .s. Peter [i.e. printed by J. Lambrecht? for Hugh Singleton?],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Impri[n]ted at Rome [i.e. Wesel?] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno. M.D.Liii. [1553]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation by Robert Horne of two sermons from: Quatre sermons.</note>
                  <note>Imprint information conjectured by STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-G H⁴ (-H4).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Reformed Church --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  16th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:7578:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:7578:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Certain<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lies of. m. Io<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3+ letters">
                  <desc>•••…</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne / conteining pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> neceſſarie / admonitio for this time / with an Apologie of Robert Horn.</p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted at Rome / before the caſtle of. ſ. Angel / at the ſigne of. ſ. Peter. Anno. M. D. Liii.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:7578:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:7578:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>¶ Grace / peace / and mercye from God y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> father of our lord Ieſus Chriſte. Amen.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Fter that god had ſtriken our head ſhepherd vndre Chriſte / that worthye king and confeſſour Edward the ſixt / good Chriſtian brethren / which he threatened by his faithfull ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes long before / yf we wol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de not turne from oure ſinnes and wickednes j perceaued that it coulde not be auoyded god ſo diſpoſing the mater / for oure vutha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kfulnes but that the kingdom of God / at the leaſte for a time / muſt be taken from vs / and the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian flock diſperſed. The whiche thinge be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganne to appeare to me more plainly / when j ſawe gods booke conteininge the worde of lyf taken forth of the churches in the byſhoprick of dureſme / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d a foul ſorte of jdoles called laye mennes bookes / brought in therfore: when y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> comon praier commaunded by publyke autori<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tie / ſet forth after. ſ. Paules rule to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> edifie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge of Chriſtes congregation in the vulgare to<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge / was againſt Gods lawe / and alſo againſt the lawes of the realme / banniſhede / and in the
<pb facs="tcp:7578:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>place therof a ki<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de of praier vſed far diſſonaun te from Gods lawe / and the example of the pri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mitive churche / in a ſtrange tonge / farced ful of ſuperſtition / jdolatrye / and falſe fables / ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving nothing tolerable in it ſaving that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple coulde not vndreſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d it / and therfor were leſſe harmed ther by (although j ſuppoſe the popiſh prelates kepe it in a ſtrange language / leaſt that yf the commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſorte of men ſhold he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re it in their owne tonge / thei wold perceav it to be vaine / falſe / lieng fables / and therfor credit their doinges moche worſe in all other thinges) but eſpecially when j ſaw the lordes table / wher on was miniſtred the holy ſupper of the lorde / according to his owne inſtitution and ordinaunce / was caried away / the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> abhorred as hereſye / and for thes / Baals altares reared vp / and his preſtes and mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kiſh hypocrites / returned to their abhominable / blaſphemouſe / &amp; jdolatrous maſſe as dogges to their vomit. Wherfor j bega<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne to recorde with my ſelff / and call to my reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce / not w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out earneſt calling on gods name for the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtaunce of his ſpirit min owne ſtate / and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dition / and to examine mor depelye / both the doctrin which j had taught / wherof j ꝑceaved that of neceſſitie j muſt rendre an accompt and
<pb facs="tcp:7578:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>that w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>in ſhort time / and alſo my dutie of alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> quenes highnes / wher in j fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d my ſelfe ſo cleare &amp; blameles / that if the devel himſelff and all myne enemies ſhold doo their worſte / thei could not have accuſed me iuſtly / nother of worde nor dede perpetrated againſt her grace. And as co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerni<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the doctrine which j had taught / the more dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly j did examine it / by the holye ſcriptures / and the teſtimonye of the aunciente fathers / the more ſyncere and pure it appeared / j was the more earneſtly ꝑ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded / &amp; ſettled in the truthe therof / my co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſcience did more plainly laye to my charge / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> j could not revoke / ſaye againſt / nor diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble it / w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out blaſphemous contempt of god / &amp; moſt horrible denial of his ſonne Ieſus Chriſt. So y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> j found no fault in my ſelff as towching my preaching / but that as an vnprofitable ſer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vaunt / j did not ſo moche as j ought to have done / although j had done moche more then ſome thought j ſhold have thankes for. But what ſo ever me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne thought or ſpake as tow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching thankful reward for my labour / j per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded my ſelff that j ſholde have all thinges waied after equitie / and therfor conſidering both mine owne integritie / that j had offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded no lawe of the Realme / but lived like an obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient
<pb facs="tcp:7578:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſubiecte / &amp; alſo that the ſame men bare y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chefe rule vndre the quenes hyghnes / &amp; ſhold be my judges as did knowe that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſwerd was delivered them for the defence of the good &amp; obedient ſubiect / ſo ſone as j herd tell that j was exempted the quenes highnes pardon / j toke my journey towardes London with ſo much convenie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſpede as j might. Wher j fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d all thinges farre other waies then j wold ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve beleved yf j had not bene put in experience therof my ſelff. For j found in the place of equi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tie / preindice: for law / luſt: for reaſon / will: &amp; ſoche as ſhold have geven ſentence accordinge as mater had bene obiected &amp; juſtly proved / playe bothe the part of the accuſare / of the wit<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſſes and alſo of the judge: and gave this ſen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tence immediatly / that j ſholde other vndoo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> j had doon / or ells: what that or ells ment j knew well jnough / for j had the expoſition therof by his owne holy ghoſt. The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> my good lord chanceloure / who is alwaies ſure at a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de / perceiving that j ſtode to this that j had of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended no law / to help at a pinch / obiected yea thre or foure times for failing a mater no leſſ malitious thene falſe. And bycauſe nothi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g ſhold be lefte out that myght help forward the mater this good olde father of Dureſme who
<pb facs="tcp:7578:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>had plaid thre partes befor right well / charge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the me with a mater not only malitious &amp; falſſ but ſo foliſh / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> j had moche to do to refraine my ſelf from laughter / j could not choſe but ſmile. At y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> laſt my l. chanceloure after certain talk had vnto me and myn anſwer made / con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cludeth that it was not only preachi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g wherw<hi rend="sup">t</hi> j muſt be charged / y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whiche he ꝑceived j ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ciently defended by the kinges law (in dede j had aſked counſall of them that wer wel lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the lawes of the Realme) but alſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teres to wchi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> quenes highnes / which were the ſame wherw<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he and the buſhope of dureſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me had charged me befor / as j lerned by thre or foure of the buſhopes owne ſerva<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes / who had made no falſſ reporte of their maſter befo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re in my materes / but as they wrote home to dureſme to their companions what thinges j ſhold be charged w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>al &amp; what ſhold be my jud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gement / ſo afterward j fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d it true. And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>for vpon the monday at after no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne which was y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thirtyth of octobre / after it was tolde me by a frende of myne dwelling in London / who is familiar in the buſhopes howſe / and at that ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me frequented it the more to here ſomwhat as towching me / that he had learned and was cre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dibly informed / both that all my goodes at du<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſme
<pb facs="tcp:7578:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>was ſenſed in the quenes graces name and that j my ſelf ſhold on the morow be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mit<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted to the tower / bothe bycauſe j had conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ned the quenes hyghnes lettres / and alſo for that j was a Scot. I ſaye after j herd thes things / co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſiderig how many godli lerned preachers were impriſoned and commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded to their howſes for religion w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out all doubte / and yet an other pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tence made / perceiving that abiding could not profet my ſelf nor yet the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gregation / my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture myght doo bothe / j committed my ſelf in to the guidi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g of the lorde / and we<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t my wai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es / not makig any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> privey to my departure. Meeveill not good brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> though after that j was entered in to my journey / j were troubled with ſondry cares / but che<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ly with this leſt y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> j ſhold now be apprehended by myn enemies / and ſo geve the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that they wold have bene glad of / ſom honeſt colour wherfor they might have ſemed juſtly to have wrought on me their wil. For they that were not a ſhamed to inve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t falſe and feined accuſationes / how wold they have reioyſed / yea triumphed over me / when they might have laid to my charge flye<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the quenes realm / and y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> not only w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out her graces lice<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce / but being convented befor her hyghnes honou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rable counſall / and commaunded to attend to
<pb facs="tcp:7578:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>they eſpied a time for me. You may be aſſured a laweres wit wanting nether co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ning nor yet good will / and having full autoritie to ſaye and do what he luſt / could eaſely have a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plified this crime / and haue formed of a ſmall gnat a mygh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ty elephant. But after that the lord had delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red me / at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> leaſt for this time / out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mouth of the lyon / and ſaved me out of the handes of all myn enemies / which hated me / j bega<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne to ſtudye with my ſelf / and mor dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſidre / to what end God had wrought thus my deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce / which was not that j ſholde now lyve as one that had no regard of gods glorye / nor of myn owne dutye. But that as j was appoyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted to be a workma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in his vinyeard / &amp; a watch man over the houſe of Iſrael / ſo j ſhold now moſt earneſtly hunte thes wild ſwyne that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroieth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lordes vinyeard / gather together / ſo moche as in me liethe the lordes ſhepe / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> now are diſperſed thorow out montaynes / hilles / &amp; groves / and to geve them warning of the fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſwerd that hangeth over their heades.</p>
            <p>Which thing j ſhall not ceaſe to do / by the ayd of Gods moſt holy ſpirit.</p>
            <p>But for ſo moche as j know ryght wel y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d papiſtes / whos mouthes ar full of bitternes a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d curſed ſpeache wil not ceaſe yea out of their pul<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>petes
<pb facs="tcp:7578:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>/with boſting &amp; gloriouſe wordes to carp &amp; ſclandre me for my ſodei<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> deꝑture / as though ther by they had vanquiſhed &amp; overcome gods truth whiche j had ſet forth: &amp; my kinſfolkes &amp; frendes will moche lament my ſtate / taki<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g this to vnki<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dnes that j wold not make them privey of my purpoſe / thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ki<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge that thei ſhold have tur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned my mi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de: and alſo whiche moveth me moſt of all / the weak flock of Chriſte who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> j had fed with the true doctrin of the goſpel / may by the ſubtill perſwaſions of the crafty hypocrites / be brought i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> doubt of the veritie therof as though j my ſelfſhold have forſaken jt &amp; ther by be of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended / and be brought from god: j ſay for thes cauſes / j thought it beſt to anſwer the maliti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous hypocrits whos mouthes although j could not ſtop / yet at the leaſt they ſhold not herafter ſaye but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thei were warned if y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thei wold not ceaſe to ſpeak that thei ought not they ſhold he<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they wold not / &amp; here by to ſatiſfy my kiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folk &amp; frendes / who j know of frendſhip and lo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ving kindnes look vpon my mater w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a wrong tie, and alſo to admoniſh the weak chriſtian bre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thren both to beware of the leven of the diſſem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bling hypocrites / whom although they be clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed in lames ſki<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes / yet by their fruites / they may know them to be ravening wolves / &amp; alſo
<pb facs="tcp:7578:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>firme them ſelves in that doctrine which j have preached vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / whiche alſo they have receaved / &amp; not to be eaſely caried away into a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other contrarie / although an angel ſhold co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me from heven and preache it to them. Who ſo will adviſedly behold / the ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ners &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ditiones of the ſcribes a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d phariſes whileſt Chriſt walked here vpon earth / what ſhyftes &amp; practiſes they vſed to maintain their cloked holines / their dir<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ty traditiones / and vainglorious eſtimation / &amp; therfor to deface Chriſte / &amp; to ſuppreſſ his holy word / and alſo will w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> judgement co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pare our pa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>piſh prelates w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the whole rableme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of their chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens vnto them / ſhall plainly ſe ours ſo likei<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ditiones &amp; practices / and ſo lyvely repreſent as it were the phyſnamie of their old au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cetours y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> phariſes / that he wold ſaye &amp; affirm that they were eve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſelf ſame riſen from death to lyf a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gaine. Yea yf buſhop Caiphas were here in his owne ꝑſon he wold for joye burſt out &amp; ſaye as Demea ſaid by his ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne Cteſipho: <hi>Oh oh la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chrumo gaudio, laudo, patriſſat, ſaluos ſit: ſpero, eſt ſimilis maioru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> For what was in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> phariſes of old time / wheri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ours now do not excell the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? What <expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abpri"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>pri</ex>
               </expan>de / what vai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>glorie / hypocriſy / truſt in their own righteouſnes / glo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rie in their workes of devotio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / covetouſnes / tra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ditiones / 
<pb facs="tcp:7578:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>miſco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtruing of gods law / ſuꝑſtitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / hatred of the true religion / ꝑſequutinge of the prophetes of Chriſte and of his apoſtles / ſclan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering of Chriſte: to be ſhort / what wickednes ether in ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ners or in religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> can be fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> but that the like and moche more doth plai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly ap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pear in ours? yea ours have found out for vs an infinite rablement of jdolatries which they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver herd of and wold have abhorred / as maſſes invocation of ſainctes / worſhipping of images &amp; ſoche like. But they coulde never away w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Chriſte nor his apoſtles but alwaies ſpak evel of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / &amp; of the goſpel by cauſe it rebuked their vices: &amp; what is the cauſe that our buſhopes &amp; preſtes may not now abide the ſelf ſame doctri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne nor the preachers therof but for y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloſe their hypocriſie and proude diſſembling w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> god &amp; the world? What will they now ſay by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> doctrine and the preachers therof? What ſhall now be the talke in alhouſes / tabernes / &amp; bank quetes / what ſhall now a ſort of lewd preſtes ja<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gle in their aſſembles at merketes when they have all their cuppes in / what ſhall now anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtes championes blouſter and blow out at Paules croſſ and els where / but that ſoche pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>achers as had vſed that place now of late years were carnall and fleſhly goſpellours / ſoche as
<pb facs="tcp:7578:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>wold not lyve chaſt / ſet naught by faſting and praier / and preached carnally carnall libertie / ſoche as ſpak to pleaſe men for profet &amp; promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſake / laſt of all ſoche as were ra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>k ſeditious heretiks / their doctrine was new / againſt the teaching of the catholik church / and at the laſt they bega<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne to ſuſpect it themſelves / and ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>for durſt not abide by it but ranne their waye out of the realme. Shall not this be the ſum of their brawlinge divinitie? But how moche ar we bound to our hevenly maſter Ieſus Chriſt that both gave vs warning y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they ſhold thꝰ en treat vs / and alſo for our confort / that he ſhold taſt of this kindnes before vs.
<note place="margin">Mat. x.</note> Ther is no diſci<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple better then his inſtructour / nor no ſervant above his maſter / it may ſuffice y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcholer to be as his teacher and the ſervaunt as his maſter. Yf they have called y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> maſter of the houſhold be elzebul / how moche more his houſhold ſervau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes. But fear them not ſaith Chriſt. But when thes ſpirituall preachers call vs carnall goſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours what mea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thei ther by? Meane thei that we be ſinners / &amp; that our fleſh is not ſo ſubdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed / but that it will luſt againſt the ſpirit? Or mean they that we have pleaſure in ſinne and in ſinners? Or they call vs ſinners becauſe we could not lyve chaſt / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is / godlily w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out a wif?
<pb facs="tcp:7578:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>If they mean after the firſt ſorte / we confeſſ with the publican / that we be ſinners / and ſay with .ſ. Paul / that the fleſhe ſtriveth againſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpirit / &amp; y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſpirit agai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fleſhe / in ſo moch y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we do not thos thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which we wold faine do. If thei vndreſtand their carnall goſpellars af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ſorte / we have to thank them; that thei will both ſhew plai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly whos childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thei ar (for here in thei reſemble the old phariſes) &amp; alſo that thei will ſerve vs here in as the phari<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſes did Chriſt / for the ſelf ſame thinge was in this wiſe laied to his charge of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / and hathe continued a commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> practice ſence that time till now / and is not like to decaye in thes mennes handes / but if it be againſt ther will. After our ſaviour Chriſt had dimiſſed Ioannes diſciples and preached to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people / thei praiſed god / but the phariſes and the laweres diſpiſed gods cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſall / and ſaid / tuſhe he is but a gloto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / and a ſwil boull / a boulſterar of publicans and ſinners. This was a common obiection and ſclander y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the phariſes vſed to deface Chriſtes preachi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g / &amp; diſſwade the people fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it / for he receiveth / ſaye thei / ſinners / and eateth with them.</p>
            <p>What were thes complaints and ſclanderous accuſationes wherw<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thei went aboute to bri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge Chriſte in hatred of the people / but the ſelf ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me
<pb facs="tcp:7578:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>that now is obiected againſt vs? Wherfor / ſaye thei / do not thy diſciples faſt? Wherfor do thei y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which is not leafull to do on the ſaboth? We and Ioans diſciples faſt. No no even as he is him ſelf / ſoche ar his diſciples. He is wholy geven to ſerve the bealy / he faſteth not / he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glecteth the ſaboth / he ſetteth naught by prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er / he is a carnall man wholy geven to carnall libertie and to preache the ſame / &amp; ſoche ar all his diſciples. But we faſt / we pray / we chaſti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce our ſelves / we ar not like thes men / we faſt twiſe a weeke / we ar not ſo carnall as this ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / and his diſciples. Were not thes the goodly &amp; holy perſwaſiones of the old Phariſes againſt Chriſt and his doctrine? Did thei not in defa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing of Chriſt and his diſciples avau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce &amp; ſet vp them ſelves? Did thei not by this colour of cal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ling Chriſt ſoche a preacher of carnall libertie / crepe in to the conſciences of the ſimple / ther to place them ſelves ſurely / vndre the pretence of a more perfect holynes? And what meane our phariſaicall hypocrites by termi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> preachers of Chriſtes goſpel carnall preachers of libertie but the ſelf ſame thinge? But this is to be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of thes hypocrites in all their ſermo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s / when thei thus raill agai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt the preachers / it is to this end to diſwade the people from the doctrine of
<pb facs="tcp:7578:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>only ſalvation by Chriſt / and to kepe this eſti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mation of them ſelves / that thei be holy / pure and godly lyvers / and therfor men muſt here and folow the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / al other ar but carnall ſinners. In this wiſe the phariſes perſwaded the bli<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de man / who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Chriſt reſtored to his ſight againe / ſaing / Geve God the praiſe as for this manne we know is but a ſinner.
<note place="margin">Ioan. ix.</note> As though thei ſhold have ſaid / beleve vs / folow our doctrin / be our diſciple / for we be holy / we ſerve god / we kepe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ordinau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of our mother the holy church: and to maintaine this their hypocriſie w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> all / when other ſhyftes failed / thei tell a falſe lye on Chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſte to bri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g him in hatred / ſaing he is a ſinner / and that thei know it ſo to be. You mai be ſure thes honeſt men wold not ells have ſaid it.</p>
            <p>But if thei ſhold have hem examined what ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne thei knew by him / thei ſhold have had no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to ſaye. And what j praye youe knoweth our religious phariſes by the prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers whom thei call carnall / ſavi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g that which is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſed / that we be all ſinners / and have ne<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de of gods mercy? Do thei know vs to be dron<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kerdes / theves / murtherours / whormongers co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon brawlers / or ſoche open offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dours as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gregation toke offence by our living / if thei do let them openly rebuke it / that other may be
<pb facs="tcp:7578:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>afeard to do the like:
<note place="margin">i. Tim. v.</note> let them prove it by two or thre witneſſes after .ſ. Paules rule / &amp; j for my parte ſhall not only make open confeſſion / but alſo ſhall make ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſatiſfactio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as the ordre was in the church of auncient time. If thei have no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne of al thes thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gs to charge vs w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> all (if thei had we ſhold have herd tell of it or now) tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ks to god for his mercy to warde vs / for this was only his work in vs / &amp; god grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t thes vnſhame faſt hypocrites true repentaunce / and amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of their lyves / for a nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bre of them be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious tabernhaunters / comon brawlers / ve<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ray dronkerds / known ſodomites / and mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtly proved whormongers. And if thei will ſay this is ſpoken of malice / j proteſt befor god that is not truly ſaid / for j do not name them / bycauſe j love the me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>n although j hate their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ditiones. As to wching faſting / praier / and preaching libertie / when did ever any preacher ſpeak againſt true praier / Chriſtian faſti<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g / or ſet men at libertie to ſinne / but allwaies invei<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>hed againſt abuſes in popiſh praier and faſti<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g / as Chriſte rebuked the praiers and faſtings of the phariſaicall hypocrits / which in dede was all one with thes mennes praiers and faſti<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gs. And the libertie we preached was not to geve y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fleſh occaſion to ſinne / but to confort by the
<pb facs="tcp:7578:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>death of Chriſte the conſcience overcharged &amp; looden with ſinne and ſoche bordens of phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaicall traditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s / as thei were not hable to bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re. But this j know wel thei will charge me w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> all, and many others / that herin j ſhewed my ſelf a carnall preacher / for that j did not lyve a fool lyf without mariage as thei do. If thei ly<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ve chaſte without mariage / let them geve god thanks therfore / j do not envye them that gyft of god. But ſurely god gave not me that gyft / that j could lyve a virginall chaſte lyfe / but af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the maner of hypocrites / and therfore did entre in to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy ſtate of matrimonye / which is honourable amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g all me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / to the end j might ſerve god in pure chaſtitie of matrimony.
<note place="margin">Heb. xiij</note> And wher as thei ſaye that although it be the gyft of god / yet may we attain it yf we will faſt and praye for god hath made vs a promiſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he will here oure praiers / and graunt our petitiones. I graunt he will ſo do yf we aſk after his will / and if that the thing we crave appear to him y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it be profitable for vs / for he knoweth before we aſke what thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g we have nede of. And j dou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bte whether all the preſtes that ſaye / thei have chaſtitie / by this that thei praie and faſt / as thei ſay / optaine and have it or no? We rede in the ſcripture of many godly men / that earneſtly &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:7578:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>faithfully begged of god that thing which thei opteined not / and yet god herd them and loved them / but he knew that to graunt their petitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was not ſo profitable for them.<note place="margin">ij. Cor. xij.</note>
As .ſ. Paule te<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtifieth of him ſelf / how he was vexed with the prick of the fleſhe / the devels meſſinger / he did deſire the lord thriſe to be delivered ther from / but he opteined not / but had the aſſiſtaunce of gods grace promiſed / wher withall he was bid den to be conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. I wil not now entre in to the diſputation of this mater / j may be ſo occaſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned that j ſhal ſpeak of it another time. But j wil heri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> purge myſelf of this crime wher of j &amp; my felowpreachers ar accuſed as carnall / be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we ar maried / and j will purge my ſelf af<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter the ordre of the canon law / as j ſaw it put in practiſe once in Cambrige for the purgatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of an holy and learned virgin / if all vnmaried preſtes be virgins. The ordre was that bei<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g ac<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cuſed of whordom / fower or five as honeſt as him ſelf / and of no lower degre in the vniver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie / muſt after he hym ſelf have taken an othe that he is no whormonger / ſwear y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they think his othe to be true. Whiche done / y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mater ſtan deth clear / and he may juſtly take an action of ſclander againſt them that accuſed him.</p>
            <p>Now do j affirme befor my judge Ieſus Chriſt
<pb facs="tcp:7578:11"/>and his wholl church / that j have not ſinned / bycaus j tok a wif / and therfor am falſly accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed as a carnall or fleſhly man for ſo doinge: &amp; for my purgation herin and to prove my ſaing to be true in dede / and alſo to approve my doi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g herin / j take witneſſ to the law of god / the law of nature / and the civil lawes till thre hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dred years after Chriſtes aſcenſion / the example of Chriſtes apoſtles / ſ. Paules cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſall to the Co<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rinthians and in many other places / the coun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cell of Nice / and all the fathers of the church to the ſecond Carthage cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cell / which was fowr hundred and twenty years after Chriſtes aſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſion. Yf thes ſuffiſe not or ells may be excepted agai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt / when j here it j ſhall anſwer it. Yf thes be allowable and ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t then am j falſly accu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed / for all thes teſtifie plai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly that it is lawful and godly and in no wiſe forbidden but that a preſte may mary. Wherfor j end with this ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of .ſ. Auguſtin / <hi>queſt.nou. &amp; veter. teſt. queſt. c. xxvij. Talis eſt enim quoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ver<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſutia, quia vt ſanctitatis &amp; caſtimoniae, ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tores ſe ſimulent, nuptias eſſe dicunt dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nandas, vt per hoc commende<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tur, &amp; popu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lum à veritate auertant.</hi> Soche is / ſaith .ſ. Au<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtine / y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſubtiltie of ſom me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / becauſe thei wold faine them ſelves lovers of holines and chaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie / 
<pb facs="tcp:7578:11"/>thei ſaye mariages ar to be da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ned / that by this meanes thei might be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mended / and tur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne the people from the truthe. Mark that .ſ. Au<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>guſt. noteth thes men of hypocriſie / ſubtiltie / of ſeki<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g worldly praiſe / and deceiving the peo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple. Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſidre alſo that the mariages of preſtes were not forbidden in his time / but then this painted holines beganne as you may perceive by his wordes / and was co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>firmed by the ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d Carthage cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cel ſhortly after his death. Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thes ſubtil hypocrites who condemne holy ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trimony as carnalitie / and feine them ſelves chaſte lyvers to be eſtemed in the world / and that thei may the rather deceive y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſimple peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple / have ro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne to thei be wearye in this raſe / then heape thei this on alſo to aggravate y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter / and make vs mor odious vnto the people / that all our preaching was but flatterye / to pleaſe the magiſtrates and the nobilitie / that we might therby avau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce our ſelves &amp; clyme to ꝓmotion: but here muſt you note by the way: or ells their tale is not worth a fart / ſaving your revere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> look what crimes ſoever thei lai to vs thei the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelves be clear &amp; free fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / &amp; thei be repleniſhed w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trarie v<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:aber"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>er</ex>
               </expan>tues. We ar carnall / thei ar ſpiritual / we ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not lyve w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out wives / thei live chaſte v<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:aber"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>er</ex>
               </expan>gi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s our ladies huſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des / 
<pb facs="tcp:7578:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>we doo no good works / all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world mai wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dre of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>ir good works / we preached to plea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>i ſpar no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / we ſought to live jdlely &amp; delicatly / y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>y ſtudye / they preache to their flok daylye / we ſought for promotion / &amp; wold heap vp livi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g vpon livi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g / y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>i wil none yf you wil ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve it the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / or at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſte thei wil have but one at once: if thei thought y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> you wold not thus eſteme &amp; judge of them / thei wold no more impute vnto vs thes faultes / for thei ſhold but looſe their labour / &amp; miſſe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g thei hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted after. I dare ſay their owne co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces doth accuſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of belie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g vs when thei ſay we flattred the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates. The rulers the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelves toke vs ſo mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trarye to flatterars &amp; me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pleaſers / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thei did moche blame vs of to bold &amp; plain rebuki<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g their ſinnes / i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo moche thei wold not at the laſt here no moo ſermones / whiche was a manifeſt toke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> gods plage was at ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d / as i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dede it ſhort<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly folowed / vpon the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; the wholl realme. And for the lordly loyteri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g prelates w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> all their ken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel of du<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me dogs / j truſt thei will bear vs wit<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſſ we flattred the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> no deal. Who the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> did we go about to pleaſe / y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> poore ſort? Ther was no ꝓmotio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nor ꝓfet to be wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. God knoweth &amp; let y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world judge / whether we ſought more to pleaſe me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; to ꝓcureto our ſelves ꝓmotio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / honour / eſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>timatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb facs="tcp:7578:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>/ eaſe / &amp; ꝓfe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>or y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>i y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> now wipe their ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des ſo clean. But let them wipe their handes ſo cleane as thei ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>n / let them ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dle the mater ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo coni<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gly in charging other with their ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne faultes / yet will they be wraye them ſelves when they goo moſt about to cover &amp; hide their faultes. But her in do we reioyſe that our caſe is at this preſent w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thes as .ſ. Paules was w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the Galathians and the Theſſalonians. for after he had inſtructed them perfectly &amp; truly in the doc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trine of ſalvation / ther entred in among them falſſ teachers which did not only poiſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the good doctrine of the goſpell which thei had received / w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> obſervationes of Moſes law / &amp; ſuꝑſtitious ceremonies / but alſo the rather to bring their wicked purpoſe to paſſ / did ſclandre .ſ. Paul of flattery and covetouſnes: &amp; therfor he writeth to both the congregations and purgeth him ſelf of that falſſ accuſation.
<note place="margin">Gal. j.</note> ſaing to the Galathians now whether goo j about to pleaſe men or no?
<note place="margin">j. Theſſ. ij.</note> &amp; to the Theſſalonians we ſpeak vnto you not as men pleaſars / but to pleaſe god who trieth our hartes. Nether have j lived among you at any time with flattering wordes / as you know nother by occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of covetouſnes / god is witne<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe, nether ſeki<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge praiſe of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / nother of you nor of others. We had inſtructed y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people &amp; taught
<pb facs="tcp:7578:13"/>y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pure doctrine of gods worde / we had laid no other foundation but Ieſus Chriſte / and in co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth a ſort of falſſ teachers / and doth not only treade downe the doctrine of Chriſt / and fill al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ful of ſuperſtition / jdolatrie and falſſ religion / but to bring this the rather to paſſ / doo accuſe vs of thos crimes thei them ſelves ar only giltie in. this hath bene the practiſe of all heretikes &amp; falſe teachers / ſence the beginning as doth wel appear to them that ar exerſiſed in the hiſtories of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church / whome thes hypocrites do folow ſo near / and have learned their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ning ſo ꝑfect<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly / that thow maiſt eaſely perceave y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> greke pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>verbe truly verefied in them / <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> / <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. But what mervaill is it / though y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>i now raill &amp; rage againſt the miniſters of gods worde / call them heretikes / ſeditious / &amp; new fangled felowes / when their auncetours y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>riſes did the ſame againſt Chriſt and his apoſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les: wherin thes antichriſtes birds wold not be one foote behind them yf thei durſt for the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple / who wold not ſuffer Chriſt to be evel ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of by name. But that thei dare not attempt agai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt Chriſt by name / thei will doo agai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt his holy worde vndre the name of new learning / &amp; new preachi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g againſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> faith of our mother ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly church. Doo thei name it new learning by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb facs="tcp:7578:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>thei have not be wonted vnto it / but now of late years? So may Chriſt be called vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a new Chriſt / bycauſe thei were never acquai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hime. Now many of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>m have this acquai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Chriſt / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thei know &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſ him to be the only ſatiſfaction for our ſi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes / y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> only rede mer / y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> o<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly mediatour / our only ryghteouſnes y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> he offred vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> croſſ ous for all / did mak by y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> one oblation / not to be iterated / a full &amp; ꝑfect ſacrifice for all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſinnes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wholl worlde. Thei will ſaye y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thei have bene ſo trained vp in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> knowlege of Chriſte y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thei know &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſ all this to be true. And thus farr were well co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tent to folowe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> late kings procedings. Yea thei fo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lowed it as a curriſh dogge doth folow whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he is drawe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> againſt his will: then he draweth bak w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> all his force to pull his neck out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> coller / &amp; yf y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> will not be / he gooth on ſnatching &amp; gna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing the ba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de &amp; ceaſeth not till he have gnawe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it in ſondre. Or doo thei name it new bycauſe their holy father the pope / thei &amp; his wholl clar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gie / doth ſo judge it &amp; can in no wiſe brook it. In this ſence Chriſt him ſelf called it new lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning when he anſwered Ioans diſciples their queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of theirs &amp; the phariſes faſt. For when thei miſliked his doctrine bycauſe it was vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly agai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt them &amp; thei could in no wiſe awai w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>al
<pb facs="tcp:7578:14"/>Chriſt ſheweth this reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>ir offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce / olde rot<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ten veſſells ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hold no new wine. This new wi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne of the goſpel ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not abide in a popiſh hart / re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleniſhed w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſuꝑſtition / jdolatrie / &amp; falſſ religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on but it muſt nedes beſpued out agai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or ells y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> veſſells will vtterly burſt in ſundre. But they call it new learning &amp; therfor the teachers ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of heretikes / bycauſe it is but a new kinde of he<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>reſies found out of late years by the germanes &amp; had bene alwaies / &amp; is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demned by the holy church. God hath bleſſed the germanes / his na<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me be praiſed for it / wondrefully w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ſyncere knowlege of his truth / &amp; thei doo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinew ther in / &amp; dayly encreace / although our e<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gliſh hypo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>crites brute abrode the contrarie. But yet they were not the firſt inve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tours therof / for thei her in have taught nothing ells but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thei received of Chriſt / &amp; was the learning of the church tyll antichriſt of Rome waxed ſo ſtrong that he ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed Chriſt &amp; his goſpel. And this doctrine which thei call hereſie is not at any time co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned by the church of Chriſt / but by the church of antichriſt / as ſhall plainlye be proded when thei have decreed agai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt any particular ꝑte ther of. But this muſt not be for gotten y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> youe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thei ſpeak of the church / although thei name it Chriſtes church / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hath alwaies co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>demned
<pb facs="tcp:7578:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>this doctrine / thei mean in veray dede a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gregation of huſhopes / monkes &amp; friers / ſworne ſouldiours to antichriſt the pope. And think youe this church will decree any thing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it ſelf?. And wher thei will defende them ſelves w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the reaſon of long auncient cuſtom / j anſwere w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> .ſ. auguſt. <hi>lib. de baptiſ. paruul.</hi> &amp; it is recited i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the popes decrees for a decree of the church. <hi>diſt. viii. can. qui co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>temp. Qui co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>p<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta veritate praeſumit conſuetudinem ſequi, aut circa fratres inuidus eſt et malignus, qui bus veritas reuelatur, aut in deum ingratus eſt, cuius inſpiratione eccleſia eius i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtruitur Nam dominus in eua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gelio, ego ſum, inquit veritas, non dixit ego ſum co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſuetudo. Ita<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> veritate manifeſtata, cedat co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſuetudo verita ti. Reuelatione igitur facta veritatis, veritati cedat co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſuetudo, quia et Petrus qui circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>debat, ceſſit Paulo veritatem praedica<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ti. Igi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Chriſtus veritas ſit, magis veritatem qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſuetudinem ſequi debemus.</hi> He y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>con temni<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> truth doth preſume to folow cuſtom is other envious &amp; malignaunt to his brethren to whom y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> truth is revealed / or ells he is vnth ankfull to god by whos inſpiration his church is iſtructed / for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goſpel ſaith / jam y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> truth / &amp; he ſaid not / ja<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cuſto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Therfor when
<pb facs="tcp:7578:15"/>y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> truth appeareth / let cuſtom geve place to the truth / for Peter him ſelf who did circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ciſe / did geve place to Paul preachi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> truth. Therfore ſeing Chriſt is the truth / we ought rather to fo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lowe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> truth then y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cuſtom. Herin is to be mar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ked this / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the holy father doth geve exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple of .ſ. Peter who forſoke cuſtom to folow truth. Our prelates ſay thei be Peters ſucceſſours / why will thei not the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> folow Peter herin. Thei be his folowers in title &amp; name but nothi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de. Savi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thei denie Chriſte &amp; pluk out their ſwerds to perſequut them y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſerve and beleve in Chriſt / as Peter did ſmite Malchus one of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> came to apprehend Chriſt. And yet thei differ from Peter / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> wher he of blinde zeall drew out his ſwerd to defend Chriſt / thei of malitious purpoſe bend all their power w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> fier &amp; ſwerd to deſtroy Chriſt. And is it ani merveill though we ru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne away from y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> cruell clawes of thes wilde beaſtes / in whos handes ther is no mercy? We fled not bycauſe we did ſuſpect our doctri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e / but bycauſe we knew well their crueltie. We went not away bycauſe we could not abide bi our doc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trine &amp; prove it true / but for y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> truth could not be herd w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> indiffere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t judgment. j pray you mark this practiſe / &amp; loke yf the like were ever fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de in any hiſtorie? Thei caſt the chiefeſt learned
<pb facs="tcp:7578:15"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in <expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abpri"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>pri</ex>
               </expan>ſone / or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundeth them to kepe their houſes &amp; not to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>m a brode / or baniſheth them the realm as Peter martyr. I. alaſco w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> others / &amp; whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thei be ſure of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thei ſhall not mead<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>le / for thei were not hable to abide their lerni<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g / then to blinde the eies of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people / thei prete<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d a diſputation / &amp; call the matter in to queſtion / when ther is no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>n to anſwer the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as thei thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>k &amp; alſo when thei be already determined / let the truth apear never ſo plaine to the contrarye / what thei will decree. Then crieth a ſtoute cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at paulls croſſe boldly / wherbe our new pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>achers now? Why doo thei not now come forth &amp; diſpute. Thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>k youe this luſty royſterki<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> doth not know full well y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thei be faſt j nough / they may not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>m to anſwer hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? Yet by thos whom god hath delivered out of their ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des / although thei be nothi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g to be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pared in learni<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g to them thei have lokked faſt vpe / it ſhall plainly apeare to all indifferent men y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> their doctrine is true / &amp; may eaſely be mai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tained by the ſcripture &amp; teſti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>monie of the auncie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t fathers of chriſtes church. And y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trarie ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not be defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded / nother by gods word / the auncie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t church / norby no ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt way / and therfor thei ar driven w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhame j nough to bolſter &amp; kepe it vp / w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> fier &amp; ſwerd / w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thus will we / &amp; thꝰ ſhall it be. And by cauſe thei
<pb facs="tcp:7578:16"/>wold ſeem in the face of the world to doo it by learni<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ng &amp; the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſent of moſt part of learned men of the realme / thei gather a ſorte of bli<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de preſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es to gether in to the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>vocation houſe whos lyvi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geth / as thei call it of maki<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g Chriſtes bodye / &amp; of prete<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſed chaſtitie / bei<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſt ꝑte / vnlerned aſſes / &amp; filthy whormongers / and thes with a ſhowte of yea yeayea / or nay nay nay / muſt determine thes matters:
<note place="margin">Act. xiij.</note> as yf the maiſters of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pythoniſe / whiche had a ſpirit of pytho and ther by brought to them great profet and Demetrius the gold ſmith with the wholl co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gregation of the artificers / who had riche li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gs by jdolatrie / ſhold had bene appoi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes in the convocation houſe at philippos or at Epheſus and with their yea yea or nay nay ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve determined this queſtion / whether Paull &amp; Silas had bene ſeditiouſe heretikes: wold not / trow youe / the more parte have cried w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> alowd voice yea yea yea? oh / <hi>auriſacra fames quid no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> mortalia pectora cogis?</hi> Whether this ſtand with reaſon that thos preſtes whos living depe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deth only of ſuperſtition / jdolatrie and fals re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion / &amp; ar for the moſt parte blind ignoraunt aſſes / ſhold be o<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly judges in the waightye mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of our religion / j reporte me to the indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent man. Another practiſe / whiche in veray
<pb facs="tcp:7578:16"/>dede was / that moved me moſt to ſave my ſelf from them by flieng out of the realme / thei ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve / not latly invented / but derived frome their forfathers y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> jewiſh phariſes / &amp; yet not put in v<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re of many years. And that is / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thei will not leave a lyve one learned ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the realme whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che is not of their owne ſecte / no nor yet or thei have done one noble mane that now liveth / al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though thei wil not prete<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be the cau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe / but invent ſome other waighty matter. I muſt nedes here geve the noble men warni<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g of that j herde / by cauſe j love them / and am ſorye to here / ſtraungers ſpeak this diſhonour of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thei ar not hable to rule them ſelves and ther for muſt deſier a pollſhorne buſhope to gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne them &amp; the wholl realme. At my laſt being at Lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>don waitinge at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> parlame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t houſe of my lor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des of the counſall as j was co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded / j mett w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a familiar acquaintaunce of mine / although not of my opinion in religion / but one that for the matters of religion dothe favour the popiſh buſhopes / and is both familiar with the beſt of them / and alſo taken to be a wiſe man and of a great forſyght as he is in dede. He aſked me of my ſtate / ſaing thus vnto me / did not j tell youe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> youre religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wold not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinew? And ſo wold have perſwaded me to have geven place / &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voked
<pb facs="tcp:7578:17"/>myn opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: wher in when he ſaw he pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vailed not / he ſaid frendly / he was ſory for me / &amp; wiſhed that he were of power to doo me plea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſure: to whome j ſaid / it was ſufficient to me y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he wold co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinew his familiar frendſhip w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> me: &amp; ther vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> j charged him as j was often wont of frendſhip to tell me what he thought of our buſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>hoplike procedi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gs. Wherto he anſwered / as in maters of religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> veray well. But in other ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ters nothi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g ſo. For / ſaith he / j have entred talk with ſom that be moſt nygh of their counſall / and j perceav this by all their proceadings and purpoſes / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thei ar fullye be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to ſet vp the pow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>er of the clargie as hygh as ever thei were abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve the laytye / &amp; j have good reaſones that mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth me alſo to think this to be true. Whervn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to j ſaid / that can never be brought to paſſ. For although the noble men doo favoure their reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion / yet will thei never ſuffer them to clyme ſo hygh again. Tuſh / ſaith he / thei ſhall firſt of al help them to bring to paſſ at this parliament / that thei wold / &amp; then thei will have their he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des off one after an other. What / ſaid j they will never ſo doo for the nobilitye favoureth them. Yea ſaith he / &amp; thei favour ſom of them again. But thei love none of them all ſo well but thei love them ſelves better. Thei ſee y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the
<pb facs="tcp:7578:17"/>wholl youth of the realme and eſpecially of the noble and the worſhipfull at infected w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> this he<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>reſie and new learning / and thei ſhall herafter vndoo againe all y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thei now doo / and then the latter end ſhal be worſe then the beginni<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g / and therfore will thei chopp of the heads of the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers and therby both their children ar diſenhe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>reted / and ſhall be hable to do no harm / &amp; alſo thei may in their place make noble men of their owne kinred &amp; fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des. What / ſaid j it were to moche cruelty / whervnto ſaith he / yea yea thei thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>k it is better an inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>venie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce than a miſchieff. God deliver the noble bloud of england out of the daunger of thes diſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bling wolves. But let the noble men co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſidre how many of their owne frendes and moſt dear derlings / w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> whom they wer ioyned inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>federacye for the buſhop of Ro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me / wretched wincheſter and develiſh dre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g Dureſme have brought to confuſion / and they ſhall have ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t warni<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g how thei may truſt thes bloudye butchers. If doctour ridley wer a lyve the buſhop of Dureſmes chaplein and one hand / he wold vouche it to his face / as he ded y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> laſt time y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ever he ſpak to him / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he careth not whos bloud he ſhed to bring his purpoſe about And what wold this vnſatiable bloudſoki<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrite have cared to have wrought my deſtruc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion / 
<pb facs="tcp:7578:18"/>whom he toke to be an enemie to his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veliſh deviſes. He invented al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> waies he could to bring me to revoke the truth: he cauſed two noble men to charge me w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> preachi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g / as he ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med it hereſie / he him ſelf accuſed me that j had infected his wholl dioces with new lern<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ig / but when that wold not ſerve / by cauſe j had done nothing / but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> was co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>firmed by the lawes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> realme / he was not aſhamed to lay to my char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge that j was not an engliſhe ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>n borne: that j had exerciſed his office in his buſhoprich / that j had brought i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a wyfe of mi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e own i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> church wher never woman came be for. And then the .l. chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>celour chargeth me w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tempt of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> que<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes highnes as though j ſhold have received thre letters of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to repair &amp; make my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne appearau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce before the counſall and wold ap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pear for none of them. If bothe thes butchers had bene ſo wel knowne to ki<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g Henry the eight for rank traitours to the crown of englond / as thei were i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dede / which now thei ſhew plainly as j am well knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be a mear naturall e<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gliſh ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / they ſhold never have brought that noble realme now in daunger to be over runne &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>quered w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſtraungers: the which thing men y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> be half blinde may plainly ſee y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>i goo aboute. I never medled w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his office / j was in daunger of
<pb facs="tcp:7578:18"/>muche diſpleaſure as the honorable cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſall did wel know / by cauſe j wold not take vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me his office. And her in he vttereth his malitious hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie / &amp; what an vnſhamefaſt bawd he hath bene / is / and wilbe to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> monkes of Dureſme when he ſaith ther came never woman w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that houſe be fore my wyf came ther. For he know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth right well y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the church of Dureſme was re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pleniſhed w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> maried preſtes be for buſh. Willia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by the helpe of lanfrank archbuſhope of Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tourburye did optaine lycence from pope Hil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>debra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de to baniſhe the maried preſtes &amp; to bri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ks from warmouth &amp; jarrow. And alſo it is not vnknowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to hime nor to his chancellour nor to never one of his officers / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> every mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ke of them all for the moſt parte hath a concubine in the towne / who hath come and doth come to their church &amp; cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bre / &amp; no fault fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de / but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> honeſt men of the towne &amp; alſo of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> countrie ar offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded therw<hi rend="sup">t</hi> / but dare ſay nothi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g for fear of the great bawde ther patrone. Yea y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> buſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe &amp; his mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ks knew full well y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> j did knowe to moche of theyr jugling and ther for it was ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me to rid me out of the waye.</p>
            <p>But when Wincheſtre cam in alſo with his fallſs accuſation / (for j never receaved one letter nor token of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundment / from here
<pb facs="tcp:7578:19"/>highnes nor from her honorable counſall / but a letter the poſt delivered me by the way as j was coming to Lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>don) and laid it earneſtly to my charge as though j had bene a ſtubbern re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bell / j perceived thei wold ſerve me as thei had done others / meane to puniſhe me for religion &amp; pretend treaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: &amp; ſubornate two or thre falſſ witneſſes as thei have pleintie in ſtore to affir<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me that j had made ſome offence to the quenes highnes / as their great gra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dſiers plaide with Chriſt / ſaing that he did forbid the people to pay tribute vnto Caeſar. Wher for j thought it beſt to deliver my ſelf out of their handes by forſaking my native country / ſeing ther was nother equitie nor juſtice to be loked for al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though my doctrine was never ſo pure / my be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>havoir never ſo vpright / and j never ſo hable to anſwer with truth to y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> was obiected. And therfor my frendes and kinſfolke have no cauſe to be ſory for me. For although j have loſt a great livi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g / al my goodes / have not on farthi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g left me / am banniſſed my native countrie / ſhal vſe no more the familiar companie of my fren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des / what have j loſt? Nothing / but ſhall be a great gainner: for yf to ſave thes thinges ama<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> looſe his ſoul / what hath he wonne? And yf the departure from theis / have ever laſting lyf
<pb facs="tcp:7578:19"/>to rewarde what da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mage is ther? our ſaviour Chriſt whos ꝓmiſe is moche more ſure &amp; preci<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ouſe then y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vncertaine &amp; flatteri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g glorie of the worlde / hath made faithfull ꝓmiſe / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> who ſo e<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ver forſaketh / houſe / brethrene / ſyſters / father mother / wyf / children / or lyvelod for his name ſak / the ſame ſhal receave an hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dred fould / and ſhall enheret ever laſti<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g lyff.
<note place="margin">Mat. xix. Mat. vj</note> As for living he y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> fedeth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſparrowes will not ſee me vnprovided for. Godlines is great riches / whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he hath. When we have fode &amp; raime<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t let vs be ther w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tent.
<note place="margin">j. Timot. vj. Heb. xiij</note> For this is a plaine caſe we brought nothing in to the world / nor we cann carye nothi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g away. we have here no dwelling place / but we ſeeke a citie to come / the hevenly Ieruſalem wher our ſaviour Ieſus Chriſt is / For whos ſake j counte all things but loſſe &amp; do judge them but doung y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> j may winne him.
<note place="margin">Phi. iij.</note> In him only reſteth the whole riches of gods trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure / he is the only way to everlaſti<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g lyff / wher vnto who ſo will attaine muſt ſeke it in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture / in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goſpel of Chriſt / &amp; not in the filthye da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nable traditiones / &amp; develiſh doctrine of the papiſtes. Wherfor deare brethren ſeing you ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ve taſted of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſwete bread of lyff / gods moſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly worde / take hede of the papiſtes ſo wer leven that worketh death. And bycauſe j wolde you
<pb facs="tcp:7578:20"/>ſhold not be ignoraunt / how youe ought to be have your ſelves wher ſo moche jdolatrie is o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded / &amp; howe to learne youre Chriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes croſſe a new / j meane to beare Chriſts croſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe laid on your baks / to folow him ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gly and not to fainte / j have tranſlated for you two ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mones of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> great learned &amp; godly man. I. calvi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> made for y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> purpoſe / &amp; thes have j done travail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing / havi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g no place certaine wher j will remai but j truſt ſhortly to be wher j will ſtikke down the ſtake till god call me home againe. But for ſo mocheas y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> buſhop of Dureſme did openlye to my face call y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> doctrine which j had taught in his dioces as towchi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the popiſh maſſ / hereſie / jſhall by gods grace / good chriſtian bretthre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>clare &amp; ꝓve by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> teſtimonie of the ſcriptures &amp; alſo of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> auncie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t fathers of chriſtes church / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> popiſh maſſ is the greateſt hereſie / blaſphemy / &amp; idolatrie / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ever was i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church / which ſhal be the next thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> youe ſhall looke for from me by gods grace. In y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> meane ſeaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bre good brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> our vntha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>k fulnes was the cauſe of this our plage. Let vs crye therfor vnto the lor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de / powri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g forth before him faithfull teares / &amp; he will delivere vs that we may trulye honoure him i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the gates of the daughter of Syon / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is o<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mides of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> faithfull co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gregation. Ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:7578:20"/>
            <head>A ſermon / wher in all Chriſtianes ar admoniſhed to flye the outward Idolatrie / taken out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> iij. verſe of the xvj. Pſalme: I will not coi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cate w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> their bloudye ſacrifices / nether will j take their names in my mouth.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>he doctrine which we ſhal entreat in this place / is plaine y<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough and eaſie / ſaving that the greateſt parte of thos that profeſſ them ſelves to be Chriſtians / doo ſeek out and bringe / j can not tell what ſubtle<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ties to cloke their evel withall. But the ſumm of this wholl doctrine is / that after we knowe the livi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g god to be our father / &amp; Ieſus Chriſte oure redemere / we ought to conſecrate bothe bodie and ſoull vnto him / who of his infinite goodnes hath taken vs in to the nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bre of his ſonnes: and to acknowlege withall kinde of be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nevole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce / honour / &amp; obedience / y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite which oure moſt dear Savioure did vouch ſalf to beſtowe on vs after he had bought it with ſo great a price. And becauſe we ar bound not onlye to renounce all infidelitie / but alſo to ſeparate oure ſelves fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all ſuperſtitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s / which
<pb facs="tcp:7578:21"/>doo as well diſagree with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> true ſeruice of god as the honoure of his ſonn / and which can by no means agree with the pure doctrine of the goſpell and true confeſſion of the faith / j ſaid this doctrine of it ſelve to be ſo eaſie / that o<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>lie the practiſe and exerciſe ther of ought to remai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne vnto vs / ſaving that manye men doo ſeek certaine deceitfull ſhyftes / thorow which they will not be overcome in that thinge / the which is moſte chiefly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ned by gods owne mouth. This cauſe conſtraineth vs at this time to tary longer in the declaratione of this mater / that every man may know his owne dutie / and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceav not him ſelfe / thinkinge that he is eſcaped when he is covered / as the common ſaing is / vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dre a wett ſack. But for that ther be many of this opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / whos churches ar thorowly pour<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ged fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the filthines / and jdolatries of the pa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>piſme / that this argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t or treatice is but ſup<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fluouſe / befor we paſſ any further / it is not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable to declare ſoche men moſt fowly to be deceived. Firſt when it is declared / how great an offence it is / for vs to be polluted and defiled with the jdolatours / feining our ſelves to cleave and conſent to their impieties / wear admoniſhed to mourn for our former ſinnes / &amp; to aſke of god forgevneſſ of them / withall hum<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>blenes / 
<pb facs="tcp:7578:21"/>and in this thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g to acknowledge the ſin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gular benefite whiche he gave vnto vs / draw<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing vs forth of that ſame filthe wherin we we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re holden down and drowned. For we trulye ar not hable to ſett forth this ſo great a benefit worthely jnough. And for that we know not what ſhall happen vnto vs / and to what end god doth reſerv vs / it is very expedient to be prepared and armed in time / that in to what ſtate ſo ever we ſhal comme / or with what ſo ever temptations we may be oppugned / we ne<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ver ſwerve from the pure word of god. Firſt it may be that many of this our church and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation / ſhal travaill in to ſom papiſticall co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trie / who ought greatly now to be in a readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and armed to battell. Then albeit god doth geve vs at this time libertie / to ſerve him pure<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly and godlily / yet we know not how lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g this benefite ſhal co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinew. Let vs therfor take this time of our quietnes and tranquillitie / not as though it ſhal alwaies laſt / but as it were a ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me of truce / wherin god doth geve vs leiſure / to ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ghthe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our ſelves / leaſt when we ſhal be called to vtter the confeſſion of our faith / we be found new and vnprepared / bycauſe we co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ned the meditatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of that mater in due time. Nether truly ought we to forget in the meane
<pb facs="tcp:7578:22"/>while our bethren / which ar kept vndre the ty<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ny of antichriſte / oppreſſed with moſt miſera<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble bondage / but to take care / remembrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce / pitie over them / and to praie god to ſtrenghthe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them with that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtancye / which he requireth in his worde. We muſt alſo admoniſh and ſoli<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cite the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by all waies / not to reſt in places wher me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ar faſt on ſlepe in their voluptuouſnes / but to apply dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly this thought / and will / that thei confeſſ the glorie due vnto god. For we ar not taught of god only for our ſelves / but that euerie man after the meaſure of his faith / ſhold brotherli co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municate w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his neghbours / and diſtribute vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that thing he hath lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned &amp; knowne in gods ſcholl. Now ſee we the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that it is profitable / yea truly neceſſarie ſo wel to our ſelves / as to our brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / that the reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braunce of this doctrine ſhold be renued veray oft / eſpecially ſeing the text it ſelf whiche we ſhal expou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d / doth lede vs to the ſame purpoſe. David doth ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly proteſt / and as it were doth make a ſole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vowe / that he will never be parta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ker in the ſacrifices of jdolatours / and alſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> he will ſo deteſt / and grevouſly hate the jdoles that he will not at any time once name the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / as though he ſhold defile his mouth in nami<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. This is not the fact of ſome one mean ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / but
<pb facs="tcp:7578:22"/>the example of David the moſt excellent kinge and prophet / which ought to be vnto all gods children / a certain comon rule to ryght &amp; god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly lyff. And to thentent we may the better per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceav this thing and more veheme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly be moved with the true fear of god / the cauſe is to be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted which he addeth / wherin truly reſteth as it were a certain foundation of that ſame aliena<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and offence / wher by he doth moſte greatly abhorre the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munion of jdolatours. The lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de / ſaith he / is myne enheritaunce. But is not this thinge como<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to all faithful and godly me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? Ther is no man truly which wold not glorie in ſo excellent a thing. And this is ſure without all doubte / that god being once geven vnto vs in the ꝑfone of his ſonne / doth daily entiſe vs to poſſeſſ hime. But ther be veray fewe which ar ſo affected in this part / as the greatnes and worthines of this ſame mater ſhold ſeme to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke and deſerve. Nether truly ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we by any mea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes poſſeſſ god / onles on this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dition that we alſo be come his. David therfor of good right / and worthely did ſet the fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dation of his god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynes / and religion in this ſentence / &amp; reaſon / ſeing that god is his cnheritau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce / he wil refrai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from all pollutions of jdoles / which do turne vs from God him ſelff.
<pb facs="tcp:7578:23"/>This is the cauſe why the prophet Eſay / whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he had vpbraided the jewes that they had geve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelves to fals &amp; ſtraunge gods / whom they had made / added afterward / theis / ſaith he / ar thy portion / ſignifieng by thes wordes / that god doth deny to the worſhippers of jdoles all bond and felowſhip of covenant / and diſenhe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>riteth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / and vtterly depriveth them / of that ſo i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>finitly great benefite / whiche he wold have beſtowed on them / gevi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g him ſelff vnto them. Som man will except &amp; ſay / that the prophet entreateth in that place only of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which put their affiance in jdoles / and deceaveth them ſel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ves thorow opinion and incredulitie. I grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t / but this alfo j anſwer / yf thei that do tranſfere gods honour vnto jdoles / ar vtterly ſeparated and cutt of from his folowſhip / thei alſo do err and decline fom what from him / whiche do fei<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them ſelves to conſent to ſuperſtitions thorow fear and weaknes of minde. For no man can in hart or any conformable faſhion or in wil / &amp; in purpoſe of minde / or feining / or by any true or feined waie approche to jdoles / but he muſt ſo farr go bak from god. Wherfor let this ſen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tence be thorowly perſuaded / and remain depe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly printed in our hartes / that thei whiche ſeke god with a true and pure minde / to the end to
<pb facs="tcp:7578:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>poſſeſſ him for their enheritau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce / will have no communio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; felowſhip w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> jdoles / withwhome god hath that divorce and debate / that he wold have all his to proclaim and make continuall &amp; deadly warre vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them. And in this place Da<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vid by name doth expreſſ / that he wil never be partakre of their oblations / nether have their names in his mouth and talking. He might ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ve ſaid on this wiſe / I will not deceave my ſelf w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> u<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>wiſe &amp; foliſh devotio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vnbelev<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:aber"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>er</ex>
               </expan>s j wil not put my truſt in ſoche abvſes / nor j will nev<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:aber"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>er</ex>
               </expan>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>forſake gods truth / to folow y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>s lies / but he ſpe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>aketh not on this maner / but doth ra y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>r ꝓmiſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he wil nev<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:aber"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>er</ex>
               </expan> be conv<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:aber"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>er</ex>
               </expan>ſau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>r ce<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>remoi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>es. Therfor he doth teſtifie y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſo farr forth as co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerneth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſervice of god / he wil abide con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually in al puritie and holines both of body and ſowle. And firſt in this place we muſt conſi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dre / whether this be not jdolatrie to ſignifie &amp; declare by owtward tokens / our agreament / with thos ſuperſtitions / wher with the ſervice of god is corrupted &amp; vtterly perverted. They y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſwi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (asy<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g is) betwixt twoo wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters / alleage this ſai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g / ſei<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> god wold be hono<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſpirit / jdoles ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by no waies be honoured o<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>les ama<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> put his truſt in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. But to this may be eaſely anſwered / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> god doth not ſo require y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:7578:24"/>ſervice / &amp; adoration of the minde / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he graun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth &amp; remitteth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other ꝑte of our nature vnto jdoles / as though y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ꝑte ſhold ſeme nothi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g at al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to belong vnto him. For it is ſaid in many pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the knees muſt be bowed befor god / &amp; al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des lyfted vp to heven. What then? Su<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rely the chefe honour that god requireth is ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tuall / but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> owtward ſignification wherby y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> faithfull do teſtifie y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it is god only whom they ſerve &amp; honour / muſt ſo immediatly folow / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thei muſt at one time be ioyned to gether. But one place ſhall ſo ſuffice for all / to confute that obiection whiche thei ſnatch of one word / that thei ſhalbe plainly rebuked and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>victe. In the third chapt. of Daniel it is written y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Sidrach Miſach and abdenago / refuſed and denied vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dre any maner of colour / to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſent vnto the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition ſet vp and erected by Nabuchodono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor / declaring that thei wold in no wiſe honour his gods. If theis goodly wittye ſophiſters had bene ther at that time / thei wold have laught to ſcorne the ſimplicitie of thes thre ſervaunts of god. For j ſuppoſe they wold have tawnted them with ſochelike words / you foliſh me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / this truly is not to honour them / ſeing youe put no affiaunce in thes things. Ther is no jdolatrie but wher ther is devotion / that is to ſay / a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain
<pb facs="tcp:7578:24"/>be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding and application of the minde to ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nour and worſhipe the jdoles. But thes godly men did folow a better and wiſar counſall / for this anſwer whiche thei made proceded not of their own wit / but rather of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy ghoſt / whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che moved them thus to ſpeake / whom yf we will not reſiſt / we muſt accept this place &amp; this example / as a certain rule and definition / that jdolatrie is an outward action againſt gods ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nour / yea although it procede not from the wil and purpoſe of the minde / but be onlye coloura<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble &amp; feined. In whiche mater thei make goodli cavillationes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ther is no jdolatrie at all when as our affiaunce is not put in jdoles. Yet ſhall thes men coutinually remain condemned by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſentence whiche thee mightieſt judge hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced. But thes men do contend only for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> name / o<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly going about ſomdeall to leſſon their faulte / which thei can by no means defend nor excuſe. Yea thei will graunt that this thing is e<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vell done and not rightly / yet not with ſtandi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g thei wold have this fact to be judged as a certai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne veniall ſinne. But although we grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t them as towching the name that thing they aſke / yet thei ſhall not get ſo moche ther by that they may make their cauſe moche the better. Let vs ſaye thꝰ / that ſoche maner of feined worſhip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ping
<pb facs="tcp:7578:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>of jdoles / is not called jdolatrie / yet nev<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:aber"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>er</ex>
               </expan>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>theleſſ it ſhal be a traitourous entrep<hi rend="sup">e</hi>ce againſt god / a certain fact repugnaunt to the confeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of faith / &amp; a fowl filthy pollution moſt full of wicked ſacrilege. I pray you when the moſt ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred ſervice and honour of god is ſo violated / that we falſly break y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> promiſe we mad to him / that thorow cowardiſe and fai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tnes of ſtomak we denie crokedly and falſly our Chriſtian pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>feſſion / that we be come inconſtaunt and dow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble / that we defile our ſelves fowly with thos things / whiche god hath curſed with all kinde of malediction: is this ſo light a mater that after we have done it / we ought only to wipe our mouth / and confeſſ that we have commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted a certain ſmall fault? Let vs therfor put a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way thes ſhiftes / ſpecially ſeing thei ſerve for no nother thinge but to make vs bouldre / and to geve vs greater libertie to ſinne / and doth nothing at al diminiſh our fault? Ther be alſo other more impude<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t / whiche do not only / chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ging the name / goo about to perſwade y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it is not ſo great and vnworthy a ſinne: but do plai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly and preciſely deny it to be ſinne. It is ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ent / ſaye they / that god be honoured w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hart &amp; minde. Eve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo truly if the hart it ſelff were not dowble. For when the minde is truly ſounde &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:7578:25"/>pure the bodye ſhall never be drawen in to a contrary parte. I wold know of them what y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> is that moveth &amp; leadeth their feet to the tem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple. For when thei goo to here maſſ / their legges will never be ſtirred of their owne mori<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>o<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / but muſt nedes be moved bi y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ward power of the mi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de. The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> muſt thei nedes confeſſ y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ther is in them ſelves a certain deſier and motio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of mi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de wher of thei be caried to worſhip the jdo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>les / and chefely becauſe they covet to apply the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelves after their wil and opinion / whiche ar enemies to the truth / yea and do ſo conforme them ſelves to pleaſe them / that they do moche more eſteme their favour &amp; their owne lyf then gods honour and glorye. Beſids this / their im<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pudency is ſo manifeſt and ſhamfull / that j am aſhamed to diſpute againſt it / as though it had ſom colour or lykneſſe of reaſon / yet j muſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des do it / ſeing they do pleaſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelves ſo grea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tly / and arr / as it were men dronken in their own opiniones and pleaſures / falle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> faſt on ſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe. They think this is jnough to worſhip god in ſprit / whos then ſhall the body be? Truli. ſ. Paull moveth vs to honour god / both in body and ſpirit / for they be his own and belongeth to none other. God hath created the body / &amp; ſhall it be leafull for vs / therwith to ſerve &amp; ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>noure
<pb facs="tcp:7578:26"/>the devell as though he ſhold ſeem te be the author &amp; maker therof? It were better they wold profeſſ them ſelves ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly to be maniches &amp; denye that god made the wholl ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Yf they had never ſo litle taſte of the goſpell thei wold not burſt out in to ſo lice<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tious impude<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cye. But now it is plaine j nough / that thei in no wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe know / what is the power &amp; greatnes of this benefite / to be redemed w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bloud of gods ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>n. And to prove this true / how can we look for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reſurrectione of the fleſh except we beleve that Chriſte Ieſus is the redemer both of bodyes &amp; ſouls?
<note place="margin">j. Corin. vij.</note> .S. Paul alſo doth admoniſh vs / not to be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſervants of men / becauſe we were bought &amp; purcheſed w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſo great ap<hi rend="sup">e</hi>ce / which is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bloud of gods ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>n. Then he y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> doth joyn &amp; addict him ſelf to the wicked ſervice of jdoles / doth he not treade u<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dre his fete the moſt ſacred bloud of Ie<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt / wherin doth co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiſt the price of the e<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ternall &amp; i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mortall glorie / which we look for in our bodies? What reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is it y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> our bodies ſhold be defiled &amp; ꝓfaned befor jdoles / ſei<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> crown of eternal lyf is ꝓmiſed vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in heve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. This wallowi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g in ſata<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ſtews &amp; moſt filthye defili<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g is it a mea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; waie wher by we may come to the ki<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of god? Morover it was not ſaid w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> out a great cauſe / our bodi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>es at the te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ples of the ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="tcp:7578:26"/>ghoſt / therfor thei w<hi rend="sup">c</hi> perceav not / that they ought to be kept in all holines / do plainly ſhew them ſelves to perceave &amp; vndreſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d nothi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g at all of the goſpell. Alſo thei declare y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they know no whit at al what is the powr of Ieſus Chriſt &amp; of his grace. For when it is ſaid on this wiſe that we ar bone of his bones &amp; fleſh of his fleſh we ought to vndreſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d that we be joyned with him both in bodie and ſoull. Therfor no mane can defile his own bodye w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> any maner of ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition / but he doth ſeparat him ſelf / from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>iunction and vnion / wher by we ar made the me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bres of the ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne of god. But now let thes wittye &amp; ſubtile doctours anſwer me / whether thei have receaved baptiſme only in their ſouls / or whether god hath co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded rather &amp; inſtituted y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> this ſigne ſhold be impri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted in our fleſh. Shal the bodye then wherin y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mark of Ieſus Chriſt is printed / be polluted &amp; defiled w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſo contrarie / repugnaunt / and ſo wicked abominations? Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo the lordes ſupper / is it receaved in the min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de only / and not alſo in the hands and mouth? Hath god engraven in our bodies the armes &amp; badges of his ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne / that we afterward ſhold pol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lute our ſelves w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> all vncleannes / w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> moſt foul ſpotes &amp; ſhame / &amp; ſo vnſemly deform our ſelves / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> no ki<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de nor likenes of chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> bewtie ſhold ap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pear?
<pb facs="tcp:7578:27"/>It is not leaful in coyni<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g one pece of gold to pri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te two co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trarie coynes / nether to ſet two ſealls the one repu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gnau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other / vnto one writi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g: &amp; ſhal a mortal man take vpon hime to countre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fete and corrupt baptiſme / and the moſte ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſupper of Ieſus Chriſt / &amp; alſo be bold to ſay y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ther is no evel in ſo great and miſchevous a fact? Soche men truly ar worthye / that their ſervau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes ſhold perſwade and make them bele<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ve / thei have a great pleaſur to do them ſervice when not w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>ſtandi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g / they geve them ſelves to ſlepe / pleaſurs and al jdlenes / &amp; do not move one finge to do any worke at all. Yf they ſay it is not alike reaſon / by cauſe we have nede of their labour that be vndre vs: j a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſwer although god have nonede of vs / yet for that he wil vſe our labour / ſervice / and obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce / to ſerve and honour him / truely it is to moche vnſemely / &amp; for vs the greateſt ſhame and infamye / to do all thing other wiſe then he will / and cleane to be void of the ſtudye and dutye whiche we owe vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to him / yea our ſhame is ſo moche the greater / that the worm of the earth, and an vnliving cre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ature ſhall requiere more power over vs / &amp; ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour then his creatour. But yet we muſt talk with thes beaſtes more plainly. They ſay it is leafull for them to fein and cloke what ſo ever
<pb facs="tcp:7578:27"/>they will emong the papiſts / and to conforme them ſelves to that maner and faſhion of religi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on / whiche is thought moſt apt to noriſh ſuper<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtition. Who is he then that geveth them bread to be fed with all ther? Who doth make the grownd fertile to bring forth fruit? If god do fe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de &amp; noriſhe them i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thos places wher thei dwell as he doth all other men in the other partes of the earth / why do thei not honour the gever of that benefite with that part of themſelfe / whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che is ſo bountefully noriſhed of him? Why do they rather obei and ſerve the devel with theyr bodies? Yf thes men were in any parte chriſti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ans / j wold vſe with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> more waighty and hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gher reaſons: and j wold aſke of them / to what end we lyve in this world / and wher vnto our lyfe ought to be referred. But o miſerable ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe that they whiche with ſubtleties and ſhiftes will dally with god / ar ſo brutiſhe / that they muſt be handled / as men not only deſtitute of gods ſpirit / but in a maner void of naturall common ſence. They think this is a ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent excuſe / to ſaye / they do nothing in this kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de / but for feare of perill and daungere / but yf this colour may take place / then muſt we ſay that Ioſeph ſhold have done none evel / yf he had committed whordom with his maiſtres
<pb facs="tcp:7578:28"/>when it was violently offered him / ſeing he ſhold not have folowed his own will / but have geven place to neceſſitie &amp; violence whiche ſhe did vnto him. It ſhold have bene a fooliſh fact of him / to entre ſoche perill and infamie / as af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ward he ſuffred by the falſe accuſation of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> naughty woman / ſeing he might have eſcaped thos evels yf he had acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pliſhed hir will. But we ought rather to folow y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple of Ioſeph / and alowe the teſtimonie of the holy ghoſte / who doth commend his conſtancye. If ther be no wickednes in taking vpon vs jdolatrouſe re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ligion when we do it to avoid the raging cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the papiſtes / the ſervaunt ſhall not ſinn / who for his maſters pleaſure / ſhall playe the bawde / kill / and playe the traitour / for fear to diſpleaſe him / vndre whos power he is. But j a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bide to longe in this mater / wher in (as j ſaid before) ther is no doubt or difficultie. It ſhall not befarr fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the purpoſe to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſidre in to how great confuſjon thei falle / whiche travail with al their craftes to eſcape gods judgme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. Others ther be y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> have fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d an other ſhyft &amp; ſterti<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g hol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>le / thei graunt / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ſuꝑſtition of the ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tles is a wicked &amp; deteſtable religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / but it is not all on reaſon of thes &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſuperſtitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s whiche arr in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> papiſme. As though all the falſe religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ever was emo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> heithe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / was not a corrupti<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pravatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb facs="tcp:7578:28" rendition="simple:additions"/>of the true religion of god. From whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce did y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> heathen draw &amp; tak to them ſelves y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> yr ceremonies but of the holy fathers? In which doi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g this was their great fault / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thei depraved &amp; vtterly ꝑverted thos thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gs whiche thei had re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceaved / well &amp; wiſely i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtituted of god. But yet al the abominatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>es y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ever wer in the world ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ve bene cloked w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a bewtiful title of god hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelfe &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> culture of his religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. But thos cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trefet re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ligions / had never y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dation / power &amp; au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> god did at any time apꝓve thos ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gregations / or y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> faithful me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> did vſe &amp; freque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t them. Goo to let vs ꝓcede forther. Alth<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ough j ſhold grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t the jdolatrie of the papiſtes to be vnlike &amp; differ from the ſuꝑſtition of the old ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tles / yet ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thei not denye but god ſo ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly dide forbid the religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wickedly ſet vp i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be thel / as al other ſuꝑſtitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s which were i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtituted &amp; celebrated i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>other places. Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> calves were erected i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; Bethel this was i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtituted &amp; done u<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dre a certai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e colour of his nae<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> had brought his people out of egipt &amp; iet y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> was y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>r appoi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted is manifeſtly agai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt the doctrine of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> law. God doth co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne al thos y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goeth thither to defile and pollute them ſelves. And truly y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſupper of Ieſꝰ Chriſt &amp; the popiſh maſſ arr no leſſ repugnau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trarie the on to the other
<pb facs="tcp:7578:29"/>then the ſacrifices of Moſes and Ieroboam. From whence then is this viſpenſation and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence to goo and here maſſ vndre this colour y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ſupper of Ieſus Chriſte is but tranſformed yea rather in dede deformed? But j ſay and affirme co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trariwaiſe / that all they that do fear god truly &amp; honour him godlily / ought ſo mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che the more to hate &amp; deteſt it / for that it doth more openly violat and profane the holy inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of Ieſus Chriſte / then if it were not ſo repugnaunt and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trarie vnto the ſame. Wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore let vs kepe this common rule generally / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> all the ordinaunce and inventions of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> propo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned and take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to corrupt the ſimple truth of gods word / &amp; to pervert that religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which he requireth &amp; alloweth / arr veray ſacrileges with whiche the Chriſtian man / may in no wi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe communicate / without that iniurie and con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tumelye / whiche treadeth vndre feet gods ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nour moſt wickedly. I know wel jnough how grevous and vntolerable this ſevere judgme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſemeth to them / whiche wold after their own luſt and delicat minde / be more nicely and mek<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly ſpoken to and taught. Wherin what wold they j ſhold doo? What moderatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and lenitie ſhold j vſe? Truly now j perceave how tendre and deintie they arr / j covet ſo moche as may
<pb facs="tcp:7578:29"/>be to ſpare them / but both j and they muſt be condemned ſo ſone as god hath ſpoken: therfo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re yf we will tendre our own ſalvation / let vs take it in good parte. They ſay they fi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> more ſevere and ſharp then j am / but j will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare vnto them / on the other parte / that j han<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dle them more mekly &amp; tendrely / the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the truth of the cauſe / the worthines of gods name / and their own ſalvation did requier. Which thing being ſo in dede / truly they can not excuſe and deliver them ſelves from the neceſſitie of that dutie and teſtimonie / that the prophet Ieremie doth requier of the Iues captives in Babylon whom he not only forbiddeth to come near y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> abominations of the Chaldeans / or coloura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly and feinedly to geve any conſent to them / but alſo doth geve a plain commaundement y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they ſhold declare the wicked religion of the Chaldeans to be vnto them a moſt filthye ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour. You ſhall ſay to them (ſaith the prophet Ieremie) the gods which have not made heve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and earth ſhal periſh both out fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> the earth / and alſo from vndre heve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Ther is alſo in this place an other circumſtau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to be marked / that when the prophet had written his boke in He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brue / yet he put in this ſentence expreſt in the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vulgar ſpeache of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Caldea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s / as though
<pb facs="tcp:7578:30"/>he wold by this mea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s / conſtrain the jewes / to chaunge fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their tu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge / to the ende thei might more apertly profeſſ y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hatred and diſagreme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t thei have w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wicked jdolatours. Now let our nice yonglings complain of me as though my adv<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:aber"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>er</ex>
               </expan>tiſme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t excadeth all meaſure / &amp; yet j have not at any time deſiered y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> half part of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> dutye which y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prophet requiereth &amp; aſketh ſo earneſt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly. But what ſo ever be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> maner / other of my ſaing &amp; moderation / or els of mi ſile<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce &amp; taci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turnitie / never y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> leſſ we ar tied &amp; bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de to that law which god doth geve vnto vs / And truly it is not w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out a cauſe / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> god ſpeaki<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g to his faith full / ſaith to them / you ar my witneſſes &amp; my ſervaunt who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> j have choſen. Wherfore who ſo ever wil prove him ſelfe to be a membre of Ie<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſus Chriſte / ought by al waies to declare / that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> praiſe &amp; honour of gods name doth ſo aper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain to him / that thei which by their faining do hide &amp; burie y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> teſtimonie of his truthe / do lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve them ſelves inexcuſable. What j praie you is to be thought of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> do al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>irlyfe time ſub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>v<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:aber"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>er</ex>
               </expan>t y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame? Of what ſort ar y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>i y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> do not o<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly hi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ꝓfeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / &amp; ſheweth no toke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> rof before me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / but alſo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitteth many things / &amp; thosmoſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trarie &amp; vnſemely / This y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>rfore reſteth that gods childr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e w<hi rend="sup">c</hi> live wher y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>s impurities &amp; abomi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>atio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s remai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / doo mourne
<pb facs="tcp:7578:30"/>after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> example of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> godly ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oth / and alſo ſpeak ſo frely againſt ſo many &amp; ſo great abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable vices of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / as god ſhal geve to them power &amp; oportunitie. Let vs now com to ſhew certaine ki<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds of jdolatries / which ar of moſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is daies. Emo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g which ſort / y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> maſſ is chefe / wherof j have towcht ſomthi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g before. For although it be ſo famouſe &amp; notable blaſp. both i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> abſurdite &amp; greatnes of miſchef y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> nothi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be imagined mor fowl &amp; wicked / yet ſtil be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>r patro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d for a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> evel cauſe / which do trifil forth i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this ꝑt. But wil y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>i nil y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>i / y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>i ſhal be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pelled to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſ this y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> j ſaie / y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> maſſ by it ſelfe is a denial of Ie. Chriſts death / &amp; a certai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege inve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted &amp; ordeined by ſata<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to aboliſh y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſupp. Nether ar y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>i able to denie but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>r invocatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſaints / &amp; ſuffrages for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dead / ar wicked abuſes / wherby y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nvocatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of of gods n<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>a / a thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g of al o y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>r moſt holi is ꝓfaned And y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>i who emo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>papiſt. do defile y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>m ſelves w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>s aboi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>natio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s do thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>k the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelves giltie of no fawlte. What ſhold we do ſay y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>i? It is not lea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ful for vs to correct &amp; ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d thos thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gs / w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we know evel &amp; faultie / we ar <expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abpri"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>pri</ex>
               </expan>vat me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>iy<hi rend="sup">e</hi> have y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> power &amp; publike autoritie do earneſtly defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>s thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gs. Therfore we muſt ſuffer that viole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t neceſſitie. Igraunt al this to be true. But j ſay this is not to the purpoſe. It belo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth not to
<pb facs="tcp:7578:31"/>their office to correct and apoint a common or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dre for the people / nether doth any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> requier this at their hand / yet nevertheleſſ they arr ad<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>moniſhed to amend them ſelves / and to inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te an honeſt and manerly behavour of privat lyfe / which thing without, al doubt pertaineth to their duytye. Nether do we commaund the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to clenſe the temples and the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon ſtreates / but that everie man kepe his owne bodye and hart in puritie and holines / and labour by all meanes that god may be honoured / ſerved / &amp; obeied / in his own houſe. For thes arr farr vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lyke and moche diſſonaunt / to aboliſhe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> maſſ in any region / and not to be preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t at it / when as the vſe therof and that religion can by no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther means be letted. But they repete and jte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate their ſaing / that is / that they do not denie the death and paſſion of Ieſus Chriſte / ſeing / they have no ſoche purpoſe / to worſhip it in their minde. But j do aſke of them / what is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> a Chriſten man doth confeſſ with his mouthe, but that ſame y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> he beleveth in his hart? This is plain and manifeſt jnough / that this thing whiche they do / is moſt diſagreinge with the confeſſion of faith. So that / as moche as in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> lieth / they do not only hyde the true &amp; propre teſtimonye of faith but alſo do vtterly denye &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:7578:31"/>forſake it. I will yet talk with them ſomthing more familiarly and plainely. For the papiſtes do ſay the maſſ is a ſacrifice wherin they will of<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fer Ieſus Chriſte to reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cile the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelves to god. But if this be ſo / it foloweth that Ieſus Chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſte hath not optained u<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>to vs by his death righ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teouſnes and eternall ſalvation. Let them ſeke al the compaſes and ſhyftes thei will / yet muſt they come hervnto / that all whiche go to maſſ, vndre the name of devotion and religion / do ꝓ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>feſſ that they conſent ther with. Therfore as moche truly as in them lieth they ſhewe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thei have not their redemption perfect jnough by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> death of Ieſus Chriſte. Ther be many that ſpe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ake not ſo largely / nether ſuffer their talk to wandre thorowout all ſortes of maſſes / that is to ſaye ſacrileges. Thei chooſe owt one ki<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de of maſſes only &amp; y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thei defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de: it is called y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pariſh maſſ / or y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> high maſſ / for in this y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> i thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ke ther is more liknes &amp; agreing w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſupꝑ of Ieſus Chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſte. And truly it might be ſaid not vnaptly / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> al maſſes which arr ſaid both of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> preſtes of the loweſt degree / &amp; alſo of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cano<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s / or of thos pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> have certai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> chappels / &amp; al other which ar fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded by any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes will or y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ar ſo ſaleable y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thei be ſett forth daily to ſale / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> al thes j ſay ar not vnlike to harlots which in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtewes ſetting
<pb facs="tcp:7578:32"/>them ſelves to ſale w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out all ſhame &amp; honeſtiel / do make ther bodies co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to al me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> high maſſ to be veray like y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſame harlot w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> doth craf<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tely abvſe the honeſt name of an huſba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d / to hi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de her vnſha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>faſtnes / &amp; to retain and defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d the eſtimatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of an honeſt &amp; chaſte wife. Although this ſimilitude doth not agree on everie parte / becauſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> an harlot joyned in matrimonie to an huſband will have ſom ſha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>faſtnes and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtie / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhe wil not ſet forth and make herſelf co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon to all y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> cometh: but the pariſh or high maſſ is an whoriſh jdolatrie of al other moſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mon / readie &amp; ſet forth to al mennes deſiers &amp; wicked luſtes: although thes filthie bawdes / doo colour and ſmoth here w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> this colour and ſoche bewty / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thei retaine ſtil ſom relikes of Ieſus Chriſtes ſupper. It is w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thes as w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the thefe who braggeth and boſteth him ſelf then more highly &amp; gloriouſlie / when he hath wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne &amp; is clothed w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ſpoiles of him / who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he hath ſtaine and whos horſe he rideth on. We / ſaie they / ſeke the ſupper of Ieſus Chriſte / and when we can not being oppreſt vndre that tyrannie / wher in we dwell / have the ſame pure / we muſt be content with that whiche is left to vs / loking for the helping hand of God. Forſoth a goodly and pretie excuſe. By cauſe
<pb facs="tcp:7578:32"/>they have no right and perfect vſe / of the ſupper / as though they had gotten a proviſo / they witneſſ and openly profeſſ that they have not Ieſus Chriſte the eternall and only preſte and therfore everie weke do ſeke a new ſacrifi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce / to put away their ſinnes. For all this is in the high maſſ as well as in that w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is ſaid in the name of Nicholas or for the dead. In w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thing thei fein them ſelves to worſhipe an jdole / and yet do boſte y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thei ſeke Ieſus Chriſte: &amp; be cau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe thei wold not ſeme to fight agai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt god w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out ſwerd or buckler / thei bring and obiect the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toritie of this or y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>n / as though the abſolu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion of any one manne may exempt and deliv<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:aber"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>er</ex>
               </expan> them y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thei be not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demned of god. I wil not ſaie y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thei lye egregiouſly / whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thei alege ſoch men as thei do for the defence of their cauſe.</p>
            <p>But in caſe it wer ſo that a devout and godly man / wer ſomtime of this minde / that he thought it was nothing evell to come to the hygh maſſ / yet afterward when he knoweth the truth / yf he doth diſalowe and condemne his former judgement / his latter is ſo moche the more to be beleved / for that God hath brought him / or rather compelled him to diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe the ſame / &amp; by cauſe he ꝑceveth &amp; plainly knoweth / that he is overcome in that thing
<pb facs="tcp:7578:33"/>whiche he before did greatly embrace and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe. But what nede we herin to ſtirre the truth / as yf we ſhold bloundre and trouble a water that is pure and clear. Do thei think y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> with the judgme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t and ſaing of a mortall man thei may ſtop god &amp; hedge him in? We know that ther is nothi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g beſides the truth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in judg<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment ought to prevaill with out the reſpect of any perſon. This mater is ſoche / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the pariſh or hygh maſſ is i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtituted to ſacrifice Ieſꝰ Chriſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te / and to reconcile the favour of god both for quick and dead / and alſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a pece of bread ſhold be ther worſhipped as though it were y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſonne of god. I do not examine thorowly all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s and wickednes / that arr in that maſſ for thei be almoſte innumerable. But j do re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herſe only the worſe and groſſer. Now let them y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> do but feine a conſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſoche wickednes and corruptions / waſhe their ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds ſo clean as they will / yet ſhall thei never be more juſt and inno<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cent then Pilate. But this is a mervaill y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thes good and religiouſe pariſhioners at eaſter time do ſeke ſom by chappel / or ſom mock chriſtian monk / whiche may prepare &amp; deliver vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> apiſh and cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trefet ſupper. Yf y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hygh maſſ is moſt neareſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſupper of Ieſus Chriſte / as thei ſay it is / why do y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>i not obſerve and kept it?
<pb facs="tcp:7578:33"/>But now after that thei have bene at the high maſſ every ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>day thorow the year / becauſe thei wold ſeme to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>icat in the ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the ſupꝑ a right / thei ſodenly ſhake of &amp; forſake the hygh maſſ. But we ſhold not mervaill at ſoch inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cye / for this is a ſure &amp; due puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t / for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whiche have laid no foundation at any time of truth in ther minds / y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> they ſhold alwaies wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver &amp; be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trarie to them ſelves / in all thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gs y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>y do &amp; take in hand. As towching y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſame hypocri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ticall ſupper / j know that thei be of this mi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de / that thei ſuppoſe it to be the greateſt iniurye to them ſelves y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> may be whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it is rebuked &amp; imꝓ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ved. But what ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we do in that mater ſei<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g it is nothi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g agreable to Chriſtes rule? Nether do j fide fault w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> this y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thei do it ſecretly / for j know that the ſupper was never better celebrated / nor more devoutly / then when the diſciples went in to ſome ſecret place / to flye the tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye of the enimies. But her ar two faults truly not to be ſuffered. One that thei whiche do make ſoche a ſupper and like apes do falſly and corruptly countrefet the true ſupper of Chriſte / do feine that thei kepe and worſhipe their maſſ. The other is that the miniſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter / whiche for the moſt part is ſom religious ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the rather to diſſemble the mater / doth not
<pb facs="tcp:7578:34"/>that office as a chriſtian / but as a preſt of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh ꝓfeſſion, &amp; in this thei ſuppoſe thei have an honeſt a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ſure defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce if the maſſ ſaier have not this purpoſe to ſhew the bread &amp; wine to them to be worſhipped / if he leave out the cano<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wher in ar co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teined many great impieties / &amp; if he de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>liver y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to all y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> be preſent vndre both ki<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds. But when thei ſhal come before y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> higheſt judge the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhall thei fele y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fruit y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thei ſought by ſoch gloſi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g &amp; lies / yea truly thei ought now al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready to perceav it. For j do judge thos ſame goads &amp; prickes wher w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces ar prikt &amp; wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded to be agrevous feali<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſame judg<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. Aud truly this cauſe muſt be decided &amp; plai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly debated in y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſame place and courte / wher y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> truth hath her grave and true witneſſes. For to be ſhort / thei them ſelves do know them ſelves giltye of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> mater w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thei have purpoſed to decla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re both to gods enemies &amp; alſo to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. But god muſt neds denye him ſelff / yf he allowe the ordre and doing of that profeſſion. If all the men in the world with on minde and purpoſe wold conſpire to pronounce thes men ryghteous / yet none be he never ſo ready and mightye can excuſe and deliver them from this but thei ſhalve thought to halte on both ſids.</p>
            <p>And god doth declare by his prophet / that no ſo
<pb facs="tcp:7578:34"/>the haltig of any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhalbe euer allowed before him. As towchi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the man whom thei chooſe to be the miniſter of their ſupper it is a foliſh thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g to abuſe his perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / as though thei could ſeme to make him an apte man to that office and fu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Yea but the vertue of that ſame ſacrament ſay thei / reſteth not in the worthines of the mi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>niſtres. That j graunt and adde this to alſo yf a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny devel ſhold miniſtre y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſupper / it ſhold be ne<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ver the worſe. On the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trarie part if an angel ſinge maſſ yet then ſhold it be no whit the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. But we ar now in an other queſtion / that is / whether ordres geven by the pope to a mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>k do make him apt to the office and function of a paſtour. If thei ſay contrarie that thei percea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve / that thing doth make nothing to the purpo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe / and that thei do not chooſe him in that ſort the thing it ſelf ſheweth contrarie. But let it be that thei as towching the miniſtre have no ſoche reſpect. Yet muſt j abide in that outward profeſſion whiche thei take vpon the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and worſhip / yea j muſt preſs it earneſtly / as a profeſſion moſt contrarie and vnworthie a chriſten man. For this is plain and manifeſt that thei do and will defend and cover them ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ves / vndre the perſon of a preſte made for the nonce to colour and diſſemble.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:7578:35"/>
            <p>But if thei wold rightly and law fully celebrat the ſupper / it wer their d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ietie ſo to ſeparat the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelves from the ordre &amp; ꝓfeſſion of jdolatours that thei ſhold appear in that to have nothi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g co<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mon w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> them. But now thei be ſo farr fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this ſeparatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thei aſcribe them ſelves in to their felowſhip and communion / &amp; do everie one of them feinedly profeſſ them ſelves to be me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bres of that bodie. After this thei will compare vs to the olde heretikes / that did refuſe the vſe of the ſacraments for the vices of the miniſtres / as though we do here reſpect the propre ſi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ncs of everie man and not rather the comon ſtate and condition. I do paſſ over this mater ſhortly / by cauſe that whiche is ſpoken is ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t jnough to convince ſo foule and ſhamfull impudencye. But if thes me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be ſo foliſh and dull witted that thei ꝑceave not this filthines / the word of god muſt ſuffice vs / as whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the lord ſaith by the pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>phet Ieremie / Iſrael if thow doſte turne / tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne vnto me. In whiche words is moſt plainly expreſſed / w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> what ſimplicitie and integritie of mi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de we ought to deal and walk before god / w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> out any thought &amp; wil to returne to thos thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gs / whiche we know ar not thankfull nor allowed of him. Whiche is a cauſe why .ſ. Paule alſo doth teſtifie y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he was ſent to turne the vnfaith<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ful
<pb facs="tcp:7578:35"/>from their vanities / vnto the living god / as though he wold ſay / it is to no purpoſe to chan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge ſom one olde &amp; accuſtomed evel w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> other hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſes and feinings / but vtterly to a boliſh al ſuperſtitions / that the true religion may be ſet in her own puritie and holines. For with out this faith and integritie / men never come the right way vnto god / but do alwaies waver and ar vncertai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to what parte thei may turne them ſelves. Ther be others that ar come thus farr y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they diſalowe &amp; refuſe the maſſ / but they wold have ſom patches kept ſtil whiche thei cal gods ſervice / leaſt as ſom men ſay / they ſhold ſeme to be deſtitute of all religion. And it mai be that ſo me of thes be moved with a godly minde &amp; zeall at the leaſt j will ſo thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>k / but what ſo ever their zeall and purpoſe be / yet may we not ſay / that they kepe the true rule or any good meaſure.</p>
            <p>Many ſay we may come to their baptiſmes / be cauſe ther is no manifeſt jdolatrie in them. As who wold ſay / that this ſacrament were not al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſo corrupted / and vtterly deformed with al kin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de of corruption / in ſo moche as Ieſus Chriſte may ſeme to be yet ſtil i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Pilates houſe to ſuffre all opprobries &amp; ſhames. To co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>clude / wher as thei ſai y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> this is the cauſe / why thei wold retai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne ſome ceremonies / leaſt thei ſhold appear to
<pb facs="tcp:7578:36"/>be void of al religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / if one ſhold examine their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces / the ſame truly wil anſwer / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thei do it to ſatiſfice the papiſts / and thei change their cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tenance to fly ꝑſequution. Other ſome do watch a time leaſt thei com in the maſſ whille / and yet thei come to the temple / that me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhold ſuppoſe thei here maſſ. Other ſome come but at evenſong time / of whom j wold know / whe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther thei think this to be nothing / that at that ſame time the jdoles be honoured / that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pictu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>res and images be ſenſed w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> fumigations / that a ſolem praier be made in the interceſſion of ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me ſaint / and grownded on his merits / that <hi>Salue regina</hi> be ſonge with a lowd voice / and that one verie ſide a mater is herd ſo filled and repleniſhed with develiſh and curſed blaſphemi that the mi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de ſhal not onlye abhorre the offen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> of the ears and eyes ther preſent / but moſt ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemently the thought and recordation ther of. I do paſſ over that the ſinging it ſelf in an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known tonge is manifeſt profanation of gods praiſes &amp; of holi ſcripture / aſſ ſ. Paul doth admo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>niſh in the fourten to the Corinthes. But let this laſt fault be forgeve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. If thei come to e<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſong to geve ſome ſigne &amp; teſtimonie of their Chriſtianitie / thei wil do this chefely on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> feaſtes. But the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ther ſhal be ſolem enſenſi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the cheffeſt jdoles / &amp; great plentie of ſwete fumiga<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tions
<pb facs="tcp:7578:36"/>powred out / the w<hi rend="sup">c</hi> is a kinde of ſacrifice as the ſcripture teacheth. It was alſo a maner vſed amonge the Ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tles / &amp; wherby thei co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the weak me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to denie god. And for this cau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe the greateſt parte of martyrs did ſuffre death conſtantly / for that thei wold not make perfu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes and burne incenſe to jdoles. When thes men be come thus far / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thei receave in ther no<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſes the ſavour of the ſenſours thei alſo pollute them ſelves with that pollutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is moſte grea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teſt and execrable ther. And yet thei thinke we ought / to hide and cover this ſo great wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and miſhef. But j beſeche the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the honou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rable &amp; holy name of god / that thei wil dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly marke this ſai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g of the Pſalme / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> jdoles ar ſo to be deteſted of the faithful &amp; godly man / that thei ſhold not be in his mouth or tonge / leaſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> talke had of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhold ſeme to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>taminat &amp; defi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>le him. This one word ought to fraie &amp; w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> draw vs from all congregation and felowſhip of jdo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>latours / by cauſe that we livi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g in that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>grega<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may eaſely be wrapped in and defiled. But to ſpeak plai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly &amp; frely what j thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>k of al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>s / w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſeke amea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> way betwixt god &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> devel: y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>i have double &amp; variable mi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds / &amp; j ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not fi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de out a mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re apt &amp; fete co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pariſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to ſet y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>m out &amp; pai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>m in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>ir lively colours / the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſame whiche may be
<pb facs="tcp:7578:37"/>brought of Eſau that ſame filthie &amp; double ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. For whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſaw his brother Iacob ſent by his father Iſaac in to Meſopotamia to ſeke a wyf / becauſe the wome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the land of Canaa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> did ſo moche miſtike the father and his wyf Rebecca y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thei thought their lyfe bitter &amp; irkſom to lyve amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; rather wiſheth death / he marieth anew wife / ſomwhat to ſatiſfie his pare<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts / but he doth not put awaie the olde. So y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he doth kepe ſtil y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> evel wherof Iſaac did ſo grevouſly complain / but ſomdeal to ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d the mater / he marieth anew wife. Eve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo thei that ar ſo wrap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ped vp in the world / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thei ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in no wiſe folow god do me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gle and toſſe to gether many &amp; divers ki<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds of religions and ſuperſtitions / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ihei may applie and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forme the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelves by ſome way to the wil of god / and thei alwaies kepe ſtil ſome corruptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> what ſoev<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:aber"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>er</ex>
               </expan> thei do / ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not apear to be pure and ſyncere. I know alſo right wel y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ther be in thos places many miſerable ſouls / w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> lyve ther in great difficulties and cares / w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> tru<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ely coveteth to walk rightly w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out hypocriſie / &amp; yet can not lowſe them ſelves / out of many doubtes &amp; ſcruples / w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is no merveill in ſo great and horrible confuſion as we ſee at this time in the papiſme. Yea j do greatly pitie their miſera<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble ſtate / which ſeke meanes wherby thei may
<pb facs="tcp:7578:37"/>ſerve god devoutly and live amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the enemies of faith if it may be poſſible by any waies. But what wil we? I can do nothi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g els to thone or to thother / but declare their errour and ſinne / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thei the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelves may adde the remedie. If thei come herafter to aſke of me this or that more dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly and particularly / j wil ſend ſoche curi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ouſe inquiſitours to the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon rule which ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve of god. I ſpeak this for y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ther be ſome of this ſort of men ſo importune / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> yf a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhold anſwer al their difficulties &amp; doubtes / he ſhold ſeme never to make an end of any thing. And my think ſoche men may wel be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pared to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> who after thei be taught in a ſermo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to vſe ſobre apparell and decki<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g of the bodye w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out al diſſo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lute and ſumptuouſe trimming / thei wold ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve the preacher to make their hooſe and ſewe their ſhoes. Wel what muſt we do the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? In this mater ther is a certain thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g ſet before vs wher vnto we ought to direct and conferr our wholl minde / ſtudie and thought. That is y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the zeal of gods houſe may eat vp our hart and ſo move vs / that we bear and take vpon our ſelves / all diſhonours / co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tumelies / and opprobries / w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ar done moſt vnworthily agai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt gods holy name. When ſoche deſier of gods honour / and ferve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t love ſhalbe kindled in our hartes / not like drye
<pb facs="tcp:7578:38"/>ſtubble ſone ſet on fier &amp; eaſely extinguiſhed / but like a fier y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> burneth cotinually / a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhal be ſo far fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſufferi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g or approvi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>s aboi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>atio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s wherw<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the name of god moſt ſha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fully &amp; vnwor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>theli is polluted / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſhal beholde y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>m / he ſhalbe hable in no wiſe to ſuffer diſſimulation / ſilence / &amp; taciturnitie. And it is diligently to be marked / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he ſaith / The zeal of gods houſe / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we ſhold know y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> to be referred / vnto the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ordre w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is inſtituted in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> churche / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we ſhold exerciſe our ſelves in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of our faith. I do not wey y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mockers w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſay / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> j my ſelf ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vig here w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out any dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger / yea ratherin great quietnes / do talk goodlely of thes maters. I a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not he w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>whom thes men have any thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g to do / For this is wel knowen j have here no land of myn owne. So may we thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>k &amp; ſay of al thes philſoophers w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> geve y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>ir judgme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out know<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lege of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cauſe. For ſeing y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>i wil not here god / who doth now truly ſpeak ſo jently to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / to teache y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>m: j do declare y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> daye &amp; judgme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t / at what time being called before y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> judgme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſeat of god / y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>i ſhal hear y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>c / agai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt the whiche y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>r ſhal be no anſwer / nor defence. For ſeing y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>i wil not heare him / as the beſt and moſt meke maiſter / thei ſhal then know at the laſt / &amp; fele him as their moſt ſevere &amp; juſt judge. At which
<pb facs="tcp:7578:38"/>time the ſtowteſt &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> craftieſt of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhal percea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ve &amp; know / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thei were deceaved in their opini<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>o<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, Let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be ſo wel ezerciſed and prepared as thei wil / to obſcure or ſubvert juſtice and equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie / yet their lawlike and judicial ornaments / and the badges of the great dignitie &amp; power / wherwith thei now prowdly wax inſole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t / ſhal not then geve them the victorie. I ſpeak this by cauſe counſeilours / judges / pror<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours / advocats / and ſoche other bearing the ſwinge in courtes and judgements / ar not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bold to ſtrive with God / and ſo to contend / that thei wold ſeme / to have goten a certaine right to ſcorne and mock his maieſtie / but alſo reiecting all holy ſcripture / do ſpue out their blaſphemies / as the greateſt ſentences of the lawe / and moſt hygh decrees. Thes men who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the world doth honour as certain jdoles / ſo ſo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne as thei have ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> one word / can not ſuffre reaſon &amp; truth to have any place to reſt in.</p>
            <p>But yet by the way j admoniſh and warn the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> before hand / that it ſhal be better for them / to have ſome remembrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of that ſame horrible ve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce / w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is ordeined for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge juſtice w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> iniquitie / &amp; truth w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> lye<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge. Ney<hi rend="sup">e</hi>r y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> doctours &amp; cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bremaſtres / y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> delitiouſe ba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ckettours &amp; ve<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rai voluptuoſe me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / take ani higher degre here / 
<pb facs="tcp:7578:39"/>then that thei may chatter in their feaſtes and banquets &amp; bable forth their words agai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt the heve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly maiſter / to whom truly al men ought to geve moſt dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t eare. Nether can their goodly &amp; famouſe titles pluk any man from this judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t / in whiche the lordly &amp; reverent abbotes / <expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abpri"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>pri</ex>
               </expan>ours / deans / archdecons / as chefe maſters of the game ſhalbe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pelled to lead the dawnce in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demnation whiche god ſhal make moſt gre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vouſe. Now although the courtears ar wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to gratifie men w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ſpri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kling of their holy water let them not thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>k y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thei ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> kinde of doi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tſfie god. To co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>clude / all jeſters &amp; praters let them holde their tong &amp; boſte not out their me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie wittie ſai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gs / onles thei will fele his mightie ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d / at whos word thei ought to tre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ble. Wher in their errovr is to moche foliſh y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> beleveth by cauſe thei take me for their adverſarie ther for thei ſhall not have god to be their judge. Let them ſcrape my name out of theyr books and vtterly bloth it forth / ſpeciallie in this kinde of cauſe and queſtion / wher in my purpoſe is on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that god be herd &amp; obeied / not that j ſhold rule mens conſciences after my luſt / and char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge them with any neceſitie or lawe. As for all others whiche do not ſo proudli diſpi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſe gods word / and yet ar ſo delicate and weak that they
<pb facs="tcp:7578:39"/>can in no wiſe be moved / j do moſt hertily be ſe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che them / that thei will take more thought and regarde to their own dutye / ſalvation / and gods honour / and do no more flatter the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelves / as thei have don hether to. Let them ther fore open their eyes / and rear vp them ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ves that thei may beholde the miſerye wherin thei arr. I know well jnough the evels / diffi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>culties / and ſtoppes wherin thei be wrapt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the papiſtes / j do not ſpeak vnto them / as though it were an eaſie mater in the mides of the idolatries to take vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d the pu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re &amp; ſyncere religion of god / but yf thei lack ſtrength / j advertiſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to flye vnto god the au<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>toure of al power / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thei may be made ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g by hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; learn to prefar his glory before al thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gs of this world. For j do earneſtly deſier that al faithful men w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ar miſerably afflicted in the pa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>piſme / ſhold vndreſtand &amp; know this / how y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the prophet Ieremie remaini<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g at Ieruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in Iewri did ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d this advertiſment &amp; exhortation vnto the people w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> were holden captive and op<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>preſſed in Babilon. Yf the tira<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nye of the pope and of al his miniſtres be to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſharp and cru<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ell / thei muſt conſidre / that the Iewes alſo of that time ſuffred heavie and bittre bondage / &amp; yet thei ar co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded in the vulgare ſpeache of
<pb facs="tcp:7578:40"/>y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trie to execrate y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> jdolatrie of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Chaldea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s It is not reaſon y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tyra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nie of men ſhold break or any deal diminiſh from vs y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> due honour we ow vnto god. Her js no exception or prete<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of <expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abpri"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>pri</ex>
               </expan>velege / w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hygh or lowe riche or poor may or ought to vſu rp vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelves. Let al men ther for bow down y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>ir neck / &amp; w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> moſt humilitie ſub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mit them ſelves to god. Let y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> poor man have y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> true fear of god / let him not ſay vnconſtau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly j know not what to do / leaſt god anſwer him / ne<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther know j what to do w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>. The riche &amp; wealt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hy men let them not lik drouke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſloggards ſlepe in ther wealth / &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſume in their ꝓſperitie / and aboundau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of all thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gs / as it were in a certain draff tubbe / but rather after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple of .ſ. Pau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>le / let them learn to eſtem all y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> / as dirtte &amp; dam<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mage / w<hi rend="sup">c</hi> doth w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>draw vs from godly &amp; chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> lyfe / or may ſeme any thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g to hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dre vs. We alſo w<hi rend="sup">c</hi> lyve here in reſt &amp; quiet enioyeng y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vſe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> greateſt &amp; ſi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>guler benefits of god / let vs not for get y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> j towched in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> begi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ni<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we applye y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>s thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gs to our learni<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> what ſo ever herafter befawl vs / or in to what ſo <abbr>ev</abbr> cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trie we ſhal beled / iet we may alwaies co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtantly abide in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pure co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſion of our faith / deteſti<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g all jdola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous religion / ſuperſtitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s / and abuſes / w<hi rend="sup">c</hi> ar againſt gods truth / do obſcure his honour / and vtterly ſubvert his religion.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:7578:40"/>
            <head>An homily conteining An exhortation to ſuffer perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we maye ther in folow Ieſus Chriſt &amp; his goſpel / take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of this ſai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g / in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> xiij. Cap. to the Hebreues. Let vs go forth to him without the gates / bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring his opprobrie.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>L the exhortatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s whiche ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be made to i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtruct vs to ſuffer pa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly &amp; conſtau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly for Chriſte Ieſꝰ name &amp; his goſpel / ſhall not moche move vs / o<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>les we know &amp; be ꝑfect<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly ꝑſwaded of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> right / truthe / &amp; worthines of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cauſe wherfore we co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tend. For when we be in that jeoperdie and daunger / that we muſt loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe our lyfe / we ought to be moſt certain of that thing / wherfor we entre to ſo great perill.</p>
            <p>But that conſtauncye and firmnes of minde can not be had / onles it be depely founded in a certaintie and ſure perſwaſion of faith.</p>
            <p>Ther be many whiche will vnadviſedly &amp; raſh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly ventre to dye for certain folyſh opinions in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented of their own brain. But ſoche for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardnes of minde ought rather to be thought a furiouſnes then a chriſtian zeall and love.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:7578:41"/>
            <p>For aſſuredly ther is no firmnes other of min<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de / or wit / or of common ſence / in thes men which do caſt them ſelves in to peril w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſoche hargie raſhnes. How ſo ever it be / god wil not acknowlege and take vs for his martyrs and witneſſes / without agood cauſe. For death is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon for all men / and alſo the condemnation of theves and of gods children / the ſufferaunce of ſhame and puniſhment ſemeth to be all one / but god maketh a difference betwixt them / by cauſe he can not denie &amp; forſake his own truth. This alſo is required y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we have a ſure witneſſ void of al errour of that doctrine / whiche we will defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d. Wherfor as j ſaid / ther is no exhor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tation ſo weightie / that can move and perſwa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>devs to ſuffre for the goſpel / but yf a true cer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>taintie of faith be imprinted in our hartes.</p>
            <p>For to put our lyfe in daunger / without any conſideration vnadviſedly / and chaunceably / is moſt againſt nature. And ſo to do / ſhold be thought rather raſhnes / then Chriſtian bolde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. Morover god aloweth nothing that we do onles we be plainly perſwaded that it is for his name ſake / &amp; for his cauſe that the world is ſo againſt vs / and doth hate vs.</p>
            <p>But when j ſpeak of ſoche certaintie and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion of minde / j do not only vndreſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d this
<pb facs="tcp:7578:41"/>y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we ſhold know to diſcern and judge betwixt the true religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / and the foliſh opinions / and conſtitutions of men / but alſo that we be tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowly perſwaded of everlaſtig lyf &amp; the crovn promiſed vnto vs in heven after our conflict in this world. Let vs now mark wel y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thes two reaſons do partaine to oure dutye / and muſt be joyned to gether / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the one may in no wiſe be ſeparated and diſioyned from the other. It is mete therfor to take our beginning of this / that we vndreſtand &amp; know / what is our Chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtian religion / what faith it is that we ought to holde and folow / what rule of lyf god hath geven vs. Nether muſt we only have our mi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds inſtruct with this godly doctrin / but alſo have our mindes ſo armed and prepared / that we may freli and boldly damne all errours / lies / &amp; ſuperſtitions / which ſatan hath brought in to the world / to corrupt the pure ſimplicitie of gods doctrine. Therfor it is no mervaill / that ther is ſo ſmall a numbre of men / that have a ready minde and deſier to ſuffre for the goſpel / and that the greateſt part of them / that profeſſ them ſelves Chriſtians / knoweth not the pow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>er of the Chriſtian religion / and ther own pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>feſſion. Al men in a maner ar neglige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t / and ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ve no deſier or veray ſmall / to here and read / 
<pb facs="tcp:7578:42"/>who thinketh it ſufficient / yf thei have gotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo me ſmal taſt of the Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> faith. And this is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cauſe why ther is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ene in thes no ſurety and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtancie of minde / and y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſo ſone as thei come in to any conflict / thei ar ſo abaſhed / as though thei ſhold bye and bye vtterly periſh. For w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſideration our deſier ought to be greater to pur ſue and ſerche out moſt diligently gods truth / that therwith our hartes may be perſwaded w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> out any doubt. Nether is this al to have ſoche knowledge and vndreſtanding. For we ſee ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny ſo well travailed in gods doctrine that thei ſeme as though thei were ſtained and died y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>r w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> / in whom never the leſſ ther is no deſier &amp; love of god / no more truly then if thei had kno<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wen nothing at any time of the godly doctrin / but by a certain vnſure / light / and wavering opinion. But what other cauſe is ther of this ſo great vncertaintie and levitie / but that thei did nev<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:aber"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>er</ex>
               </expan> ꝑceave in ther minde the maieſtie of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> holy ſcripture. And truly if we wold rightly waye / that it is god that ſpeaketh to vs theirin we wold here him with more diligence / atten<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion and revere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. If we wold think in readi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the ſcripture / that we ar in the ſchole and diſci<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pline of angels / we ſhold have an other ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ner of deſier to exerciſe our ſelves in that doctri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne / 
<pb facs="tcp:7578:42"/>which is ſetforth to vs / to confort / ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / and inſtruct our mi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds. Now we ſee what is the waye to prepare our ſelves to patience &amp; ſufferaunce for the goſpel / that is ſo to goo for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward in the doctrine ther of / that being throw<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly perſwaded of the true religion &amp; that doctri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne which we ought to holde and defend / we may nothing eſteme / and deſpiſe all the fravds and illuſions of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> devel / and al the inve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tions of men / as things not only of no value / but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo execrable / by cauſe thei vttrely corrupt the Chriſtian ſynceritie. And herin we differ as true martyres of Ieſus Chriſt / from the furi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſe and ſtifnecked men / which ſuffre for their own foliſh opinions. Seco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dly we ought to be ſo minded / that being aſſured of the right and goodnes of the cauſe / we ſhold be enflamed w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> this due deſier to folow god whither ſo ever he ſhal call vs / to embrace his word w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſoche reve<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rence as it is worthie / and being called bak fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the deceitfull faſhion of this world / as men ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſhed / w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> their whol mi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de &amp; endevoir ſhold be caried to an heve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly lyfe. But o moſt miſerable caſe / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the light of god doth ſhine vnto vs in thes daies ſo bright as it did nev<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:aber"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>er</ex>
               </expan> ſhine in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / yet ſo litle zeal / favo<hi rend="sup">2</hi> &amp; love ſhold be fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d. Wheri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our miſerie is ſo moche
<pb facs="tcp:7578:43"/>the greater / that in ſo great filthines and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankfulnes we ar not overwhelmed with blu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhing ſhame. For we muſt ſhortly come before y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> judge / before whom our vice and evel w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we by al means go abovt to hide / ſhall be brought forth / with that rebuke and chek / wherby the juſt cauſe of our deſtruction ſhal apear. For yf we be ſo endebted and bound to god / that for the knowlege he hath geven vs / we ought to geve to him honourable and thankfull teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nie / why is our ſtomak ſo abaſhed &amp; fearful to entre in to the batell? Eſpecially ſeing god in this our age / hath ſo opened him ſelfe / that it may be rightly ſaid and truly / that he hath ope<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned and plainly ſet forth / the greateſt treaſurs of his ſecrets. May not this be ſaid / that we ſo think of god / as though we ſemed to ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d no nede of him at all? For yf we had any conſi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deration of his maieſtie / we durſt never be ſo bold to turn the doctrine / whiche proceadeth out of his mouth in to philoſophye and vai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſpe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>culation. In fine we can have no excuſe / but this muſt be vnto vs the greateſt ſhame / yea an horrible condemnation / that in ſo great know<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lege / obtained by the ſingulare goodnes of god we have ſo litle love &amp; mind to defend &amp; kepe the ſame. For firſt / yf we will call to our rema<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>braunce
<pb facs="tcp:7578:43"/>the martyrs of olde time / and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pare their wondreful conſtancie with this our te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dre ſlouthfulnes / we ſhal finde paſſing great cauſe to deteſt our own filthines. For thei were not for the moſt part ſo travailed and excerciſed in the ſcripturs / that thei could learnedly diſpute of all maters. But firſt of al / thei knew &amp; held faſt this / that ther is one god / who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thei ought to ſerve and honoure: then / that thei were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demed with the bloud of Ieſus Chriſte / that in him only and in his grace thei ſhold put their af<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fiaunce / and truſt of ſalvation. Morover they did judge all other inventions and ordinau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / to worſhip god / ſo vnworthy filthines / that thei could eaſely condemne al jdolatries &amp; ſuperſtitions: to conclude in few words this was their divinitie / ther is one only god the maker of the whol world / which hath declared vnto vs his wil by Moſes and the prophets / &amp; then by Ieſus Chriſte and his apoſtles. We ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ve one redemer / with whos bloud we were bought / &amp; by whos grace we hope to be ſaved. Al the jdoles of the world / ar to be deteſted and accurſed. Thei came ſtoutly and boldly to the fier / or other kinde of death / and puniſhment / inſtructed with no other doctrin and more hid<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>den knowlege. And the numbre of them was
<pb facs="tcp:7578:44"/>not ſmall / as of two or thre / but ſo great that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> multitude of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / whiche were cruelly vexed and tormented of the tyrants ſemed innumera<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble and infinite. But we ar ſo taught and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed / that we paſſe all our auncetours in knowlege and vndreſtandi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g of holy ſcripture. We think in our ſelves / and it is true / as tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the vndreſtanding of the ſcripture / god hath e<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dued vs with ſo moche knowlege / as he hath geve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to any age at any time. And yet ther is in vs ſcantly the leaſt droppe of fervent love towards god. Ther is no reaſon why we ſhold noriſh this nice cowardnes of mi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de / onleſſ we wold willi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gly and wittingly provoke y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wrath and vengeaune of god / againſt our ſelves.</p>
            <p>What muſt we then do? Truli we muſt tak to vs aſtowt / bold / &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t mi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d. We muſt chefely conſidre how precious and honourable the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>feſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; teſtificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of our faith is before god.</p>
            <p>For we do litle know / how God doth eſteme this confeſſion / when our lyfe whiche is of no value / is more ſet by and dear vnto vs.</p>
            <p>Wherin our wondrefull and beaſtly foliſhnes is ſhewed: for we can not in this ſort ſpare our lyfe / but we muſt nedes confeſſ that we ſett mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re therby / then by gods honour and our own ſalvation. A certain hethen man could vſe
<pb facs="tcp:7578:44"/>this ſaing / that it is a miſerable thing / to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake and betray the cauſes why we lyve for the conſervation of lyfe. Yet he and his lyk did ne<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ver know truly / to what end men wer ſet in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world / and wher for thei lived ther in. Thei might well ſay / that vertue is to be eſtemed &amp; folowed / and that we ought to lyve an honeſt lyfe / without blame. But all ther vertues wer nothing ells / but colours and ſhadowes. But we have better vndreſtanding / whervn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our lyfe muſt be referred / whiche is / that we honour God / with all prayſe and glorye / that he him ſelfe may be our glorye.</p>
            <p>Without him / our lyfe is miſerable / the whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che we can not continew the leaſt moment but we ſhall heap vpon our ſelves / a perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual malediction. And yet we ar nothing a ſhamed for the winning of a few daies / for this feble lyfe / to refuſe the eternall kingdom / and to ſeparate our ſelves from him / by whos power we ar continewed in this lyfe. Yf a man ſhold examine the moſt vnlearned / yea thos whos witt is ſo daſed / and whos lyfe ſo voluptuouſe / that they be moſt lyke to brute beaſts / what maner of lyfe is apoynted them / they durſt not ſay plainly and openly / that it ſhold co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nſiſte o<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>lye in eating / dre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>king &amp; ſleapi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g,
<pb facs="tcp:7578:45"/>For thei know that thei ar created to a better / wort hier and more higher thing: which is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ells / but to ſerve and honour god with al ki<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of honour / and to ſuffer our ſelves as good children / to be ordred and rueled by our moſt bening father / that after the end of this fraill &amp; vnſure life / we may be receaved in to his eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal heretage. In the apointing and winning of this end / conſiſteth the chefeſt and greateſt point of our felicitie / yea al the wholl weight of ever laſting lyfe. But when we carrye our mi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds and thoughts an other waye / &amp; do ſnatch faſt hold of this preſent lyfe worſe then a thow ſand deathes / what excuſe can we have? For / to lyve and be ignoraunt of the cauſes wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>for we lyve / is vnnatural. But to forſake the cauſes wherfore we lyve here / for the deſier &amp; love to prolong our lyfe as it were for thre dai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>es in this deceatful world / and to be ſeparated from god the author of lyfe / is ſoche a bewit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching and furiouſe madnes / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> j know not with what words we ought to expreſſ and ſhew it. But what ſo ever knowlege we have / and how ſo ever our lyfe is apointed / for ſo moche as not with ſtanding the perſequutions ar no leſſ &amp; bitter / let vs co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſidre how &amp; by what mea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s the Chriſtian men may confirm them ſelves
<pb facs="tcp:7578:45"/>in patiencye / and ſo ſtrengh then their minds / that thei may conſtantly ve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tre to dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger their lyfe for gods truth. This ſame text which we have recited / being wel vndreſtonded may bri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g vs to that indifferencye of minde / yea to that willingnes / that we ſhall not refuſe to ſuffre death for gods name. Let vs go forth of the cytie / ſaith the apoſtle / after the lord Chriſte / bering his opprobrie. Firſt / he doth teach &amp; admoniſh vs / that although the ſwerds ar not alreadye drawen to kill vs / or the fiers kindled to broyll and burne vs / yet that we can not truly be joyned with the ſonne of god / ſo long as we have the roots of our thoughts &amp; deſiers fixed in this world. Wherfor the Chriſten ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> muſt alwaies / although he be in quiet / have one fote lifted vp readye to the battell / and not only that / but alſo his mi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d muſt be vtterli ſepa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rated fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world although his body be theri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Althought this at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſt ſyght may ſeme vnre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſonable / yet one ſaing of .ſ. Paull / ought to be ſufficient to ꝑſwade vs / for that we be called &amp; appointed to this / to ſuffer perſequution.</p>
            <p>As though he ſhold ſaye / Soche is the conditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of our Chriſtianitie / that we muſt neds en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tre in and paſſ thorow this waye / yf we will folow Chriſte. In the mean ſeaſon / to eaſe
<pb facs="tcp:7578:46"/>our infirmitie and to mitigate the tediouſnes and hevines / whiche perſequutiones bri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geth / we have this great &amp; ſwete co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort / that we ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ring all thes inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modities / opprobries &amp; daun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gers of lyfe for the goſpel / do as it were ſet our feet / in everie foteſtep of gods ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne / and do fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low him as our prince &amp; guide. If it had bene o<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly ſaid vnto vs / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we muſt paſſ thorow all the opprobries of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world to kepe the chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion / and alſo ſuffre death frely &amp; w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> out fear when ſo ever gods will were / methi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>k we ſhold have had ſome colour to anſwer and ſay contra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rye / that it is a thing divers and abhorring fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our nature to wandre ſo with out a guide. But ſeing we ar charged and commaunded to folow y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord Ieſus / his leadi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g ought to ſeme ſo right and honorable / that we have no juſt excuſe to refrain or refuſe his commavndement.</p>
            <p>But that we ſhold have mor earneſt love and deſier towards this lawdable and helthfull ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample / it was not only ſaid that Ieſus Chriſte doth lead the way as guide and prince / but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo that we ar made li<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ke vnto his jmage.</p>
            <p>For ſo .ſ. Paul in the epiſtle to the Rom. ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth / that god hath choſen and called all them whom he hath taken in to the nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bre of his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren / that they ſhold be like and be faſhioned af<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter
<pb facs="tcp:7578:46"/>the jmage of him whiche is apointed pater<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne and hede over all. What / ar we ſo nice and tendre y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we can or will bear and ſuffer nothing at all? Then muſt we neds refuſe gods grace wherby he calleth vs to the hope of ſalvation &amp; leadeth vs ther to by this way? Forthes two ar ſo ioyned to gether y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the one can not be ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from the other / that we be the membres of Ieſus Chriſte / and that by means of this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iunction and communio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / we be exerciſed with many afflictiones and calamities. This ſame maner of our lyfe ſo ioyned with gods ſonne / and ſoche conformitie to him / we ought to eſte<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me mor then we do / and alſo to judge it not on<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly by all wayes moſt worthye to be profeſſed but alſo to be folowed. The ſuffering of calamities for the goſpell / in the opinion and judgment of the world / is the greateſt infamie but ſeing we know that all the vnfaithful ar ſo blinded / that they can ſee or ryghtly judge no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing at all / ought not we to have clear eies / and to judge mor perfectly? It is ſhame to be afflicted and vexed of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that occupie the ſeat of juſtice. But .ſ. Paul doth ſhew vs by his example / that we have great occaſion to glorie in the ſcarres of Ieſus Chriſte / and as it wer in certain markes imprinted in vs / 
<pb facs="tcp:7578:47"/>wher with we being marked &amp; deckt / god doth acknowleg and receav vs for his ſervau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>elect. And we know this y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> .ſ. Luke doth reherſe of Peter and Ioan / that they were veray glad and joyfull / that thei were thought worthie to ſuffer for the lord Ieſus name / ſclandre rebuks and ſhame. Wher in two things may be ſeen contrarie in them ſelves / ſhame / and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour / by this that the world running hedlong in furie and madnes doth iudge againſt all rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon / and by this means doth chaunge the glori of god with diſhonour and infamie. Let not vs now diſdain ſo to be diſpiſed and to be rebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked of the world / that we may herafter optai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne with god and his angells / honour / glorie &amp; praiſe. We ſee what great labours ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſe men taketh to obtaine the ordre of ſome king / and after thei have at cheved it / what tri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vmphes they make: but the ſonne of god doth offre to vs his ordre / and yet everie one diſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth it / and is turned with the wholl power of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vanitie of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world. I pray you whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we behave our ſelves ſo ꝓudly &amp; vntha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kfully / ar we worthie to have any thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g como<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> him? Although our vndreſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ꝑceave &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>he<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d nothi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g heri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / yet of a truth thes ar the ꝓpre &amp; honorable badges and armes of hevenly no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitie.
<pb facs="tcp:7578:47"/>Im<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abpri"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>pri</ex>
               </expan>ſonme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts / baniſhments / maledic<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tions / after the opinion of men bring nothing ells then great ſham and infamie. But what doth let vs to ſee what god doth judge &amp; ꝓnou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>s thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gs / ſavi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g our own i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fidelitie? Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>for we muſt labour y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> name of gods ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne be of ſoche authoritie / waight / &amp; honour w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> vs / as it is moſt worthie / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>k we ar well &amp; honou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rably delt w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> al / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his burnes as it wer certaine badges ar <expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abpri"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>pri</ex>
               </expan>nted in vs / or els our vntha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kfulnes ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in no wiſe be borne. If god ſhold ꝑſequut vs after our merits / hath he not iuſt cauſe everie daye to chaſtice &amp; puniſh vs i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>finite waies? Yea ſurly no deathes put vnto vs were able to reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> leaſt part of our miſchefe. But of his gre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>at &amp; infinite goodnes / he treadeth vndre fote al our ſi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes / &amp; doth vtterli aboliſh y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame / &amp; wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>as he might puniſhe vs accordi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> greatnes of our ſi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes / he hath i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> other merveilous way / wherby y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> afflictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ar traduced fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſerved paine &amp; puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t / to a great honour / &amp; a certai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abpri"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>pri</ex>
               </expan>vilege &amp; ſi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>guler benefite / becauſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> partaki<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g &amp; ſufferi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we ar receaved in to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> felowſhip of gods ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne. May it be o y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>r waies ſaid or judged / then that we / ſeing we deſpiſe and diſdain this ſo excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t and bliſfull conditi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on and maner of living / have litle profetted in
<pb facs="tcp:7578:48"/>the chriſtian doctrin? This is the cauſe why .ſ. Peter after he had moved vs to lyve a godly &amp; holye lyfe in the fear of god / farr from that lyfe wherfor other men as theves / whormongers / adulterours / and me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>killers ſuffre / by &amp; by ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth this / yfwe muſt ſuffer as chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> men / ther in we geve glory to god for that great and ſingu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ler benefite / which he hath beſtowed on vs.</p>
            <p>Nor it is not for nothing that the holy ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſpea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>keth thus / what ar we / j pray youe / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we ſhold be witneſſes of gods truth / and as it were proc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours apointed to defend his cauſe. Behold we be miſerable me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as it wer wormes of the earth creaturs full of vanities and lies / yet god will have his truth defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded by vs / which is truly ſo great honour / that it ſemeth not to pertain to the angells in heven. This one reaſon well con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſidered / ovght it not to enflame and ſtire vp our minds / to offre our ſelves wholy to god / and to ſhew our wholl endevoire in ſo holye and excel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lent a mater to pleaſe him? And yet many can not forbear / but that thei wil ſpeak againſt god or at the leaſt thei will complaine / that he hath no greater regard to eaſe their imbecillitie. it is a merveilous mater / ſay they / that ſeing god hath borne vs thus moche fovoure / that he hath choſen vs to be his children / yet he wil ſuf<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fer
<pb facs="tcp:7578:48"/>vs to be ſo cruelly vexed &amp; oppreſſed of wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked men. I do yet anſwer thes men / that although we knew no reaſon why god doth ſo deall with vs / yet his authoritie ſhold be ſoche with vs / that we ſhold applye / &amp; conforme our ſelves to his will. But now when we ſee Ieſus Chriſte to be ſet for an example to vs / le<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>aſt we ſhold ſeke any other / ought we not to think our ſelves greatly happye / that we be ſo drawen after his jmage and liknes? Morover god doth ſet forth and ſhe we plai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e and manifeſt cauſes / wherfor he will have vs to ſuffre perſe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>quution / emonge which / if ther wer non other but that reaſon and advertiſment which .ſ. Pe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter geveth / we muſt neds be veray peviſh and ſturdye / onleſs we be ſatiſfied ther with.</p>
            <p>This is his reaſon / that ſeing gold and ſilver which ar corruptible metalls ar purged and tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the fier / it is reaſon that our faith alſo / whiche in value excelleth all riches / be tried &amp; approved with ſoche perills of lyfe and greves.</p>
            <p>He could by and by after our calling / with out any conflict and ſuffering of thes calamiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es have crowned vs. But as he wold have Chriſte to rai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g in the mides of his enemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es / eve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo he wold have vs alſo dwelli<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g emong y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſelfſame / to bear &amp; ſuffre y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>ir viole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>c &amp; oppreſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb facs="tcp:7578:49"/>vntill we be delivered from thes afflictiones &amp; calamities by him. And j am not ignoraunt / that the fleſh will then greatly ſpurne and refu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe to be ruled / whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it muſt be brought in to this ſtate / but yet the will of god muſt rule all our thoughtes and luſtes. Yf we fele in our ſelves ſom contradiction and reſiſtaunc it is not great<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly to be merveiled at. For that is planted and engraven in our nature to flye the croſſe. Yet let vs not abide ſtill / in that tendrenes of the fleſhe / but let vs go on forward / knowing that our obedience is thankful &amp; acceptable to god / ſo that we caſt down our ſences and appetits / and do ſo ſubdue them / that thei be vndre his powr. Nether did the prophetes and apoſt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>les com to death with minde / that thei did not perceave their will to be againſt it / and encli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g an other waie. Thei ſhal lead the whether thow wolds not / ſaid our lord Ieſus to Peter. So whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſoche fear of death doth prik our mi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds let vs labour by al meanes / that we may have the overhand / or rather that god may overco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me / and in the mean while let vs thus perſwa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de our ſelves / that it is to him a moſt pleaſant ſacrifice / when we reſiſt our appetites / and do ſo withſtand them / that by this meanes being ſubdued vndre his power / we may ordre and
<pb facs="tcp:7578:49"/>lead our lyfe after his will and pleaſure. This is the cheffeſt and greateſt battell / whervnto god will have all his with all ther power to ap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>plie / to thende thei may laboure / to caſt down and depreſſ all that whiche doth ſo moche exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te it ſelfe in their ſences / wittes and appetits / that it doth carye and withdrawe themfrom y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> way / which god doth ſhew to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. In the mea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſeaſon / the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſolations ar ſo great and weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye / that it can not be expreſſed / how moche deyntie cowardnes is in vs / when we waxe faint herted / and geve over for thes perills and troubles. In olde time the numbre was almoſt infinite of them / which for the deſier of a gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land made of corruptible leaves / did refuſe no laboure / paine and wraſtlinge / and alſo did ſo ſuffre death it ſelfe / that thei might ſeme to have their lyfe in no price. And yet ther was none of them / but did contend chanceably bei<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g vncertain / whether he ſhold winne / or loſe the game. God doth ſet befor vs an immortall crown / wheri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we may optaine his own glorie. And he hath not apointed vs / an vncertaine &amp; chanceable conflict / but doth promiſe ſoche are ward / to the whiche we ought to conferr all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> counſeills / ſtudies / and deſiers of our lyfe.</p>
            <p>What is the cauſe / that we ar ſo faint herted in
<pb facs="tcp:7578:50" rendition="simple:additions"/>the largenes and worthines of this honour / which is certaine and eternal? Do we think y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> this was ſpoken in vaine / that we ſhal lyve w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Chriſte / yf we be dead with him? The triu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ph is prepared for vs / but we ſo moche as we may do flie from the conflict and battel. But this doctrin is ſoche / that it ſemeth plainlie to diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree with mans judgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. This is true.</p>
            <p>Nether alſo Chriſte / whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he pronounceth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> bleſſed which ſuffer ꝑſequution for right eouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes ſake / doth propownd ſoche a ſentenc as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> opinion of the world wold allowe or receav.</p>
            <p>Yea he wil have vs to thinke / that to be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chef<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>feſt felicitie / which we judge the greateſt miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie. We think our ſelves moſt miſerable / whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> god doth ſuffre vs to be afflicted and oppreſſed with the tyra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nye and crueltie of our enemies. But we do wondrefully erre in this / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we ſet not befor our eies gods promiſes / w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> do plainli confirme vnto vs / that al things ſhal come to our profect / joye / and ſalvatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. We caſt down our ſtomakes and diſpare when we ſee wicked &amp; naughty men / to have the ov<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:aber"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>er</ex>
               </expan>hand on vs / &amp; to do y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> crueltie to vsy<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thei ſeme to tread down our neck with their feet. But this ſame moſt cruel vexation of the wicked / and ſo great trou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fuſion of thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gs / as ſ. Paul warneth / 
<pb facs="tcp:7578:50"/>ought rather to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>firm our mi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds raiſe vp &amp; lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in to heve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. For bi cauſe of our own natur we ar be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtudie &amp; love of thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gs preſent / &amp; ar ſo inflamed y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>our whol knowlege / mi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d &amp; cogitatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / we ar occupied in to moche levi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g &amp; v<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſing this vanitie: god / whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſuffreth vs to be thꝰevel vexed &amp; handled / &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wicked to grow &amp; floriſh in al thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gs / doth teache &amp; admoniſh vs by thes plaine &amp; notable ſings of his moſt juſt judgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> / that daie ſhal once come / whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gs y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> be now troubled &amp; confuſed / ſhalbe ſat<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tled. But yf y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſame time ſeme far &amp; lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g to / let vs flye to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reamedie / &amp; let vs not flatter our ſelves in our vice. For this is certaine y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ve no faith at al onleſſ we caſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> eies of our mi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> honourable coming of Ieſus Chriſte.</p>
            <p>And becauſe god wold leave out no co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiderati<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> might be apt to move &amp; ſtirre vs / he doth ſet forthe on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> one part ꝓmiſes / on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other ꝑt threateni<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gs. Do we fele y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ꝓmiſes of god have not force jnough &amp; autoritie in vs? To co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>firm the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>al let vs joi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>rto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> threateni<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gs. We ſhew our ſelves <abbr>wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>douſti</abbr> froward / ſence we beleve gods ꝓmiſes no more y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>n we do. Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord Ie<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſꝰ Chri.
<note place="margin">Mat. x. Luc. ij.</note> ſaith / he wil acknowleg vs for his own &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſ ſo of vs befor his father / ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we alſo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>feſſ him befor men / what ſhold let vs to geve
<pb facs="tcp:7578:51"/>to him that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſion / which he requireth of vs?</p>
            <p>When men have done all thei can / the worſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>i may do is to take away our lyves. How pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſe then ſhall the heve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly lyfe be vnto vs whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it is compared with this preſent lyfe whiche is loſt? It is not my purpoſe in this place to col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect all the promiſes ſet forth in the ſcripture to this end. Yet ſence thei be repeated and ſo ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> times renued vnto vs / we ought ſo to be exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed not only in the readi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g / but alſo in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> knowle<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſolation of them / that we might be as it wer died and ſurelye confirmed in them.</p>
            <p>But yf when y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> plage hangeth over our heades thre or fower of them ar not fufficient to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm &amp; ſtrengthen vs / truely an hundreth ſhold be ſufficient to overcome al adverſe and contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie temtations. But yf god with thes great ſwete promiſes can not entice and draw vs to him / ar we not veray great dullerds / and betle heads / when nether the ſever threatenings can work any more in vs?
<note place="margin">Luc. ix.</note> Ieſus Chriſte doth ap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pointe adaye to accuſe all them befor his father whiche denye the truth for fear of loſing this li<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fe / for whom he declareth deſtruction both of bodye and ſoull to be prepared.
<note place="margin">Mat. x.</note> Alſo in an other place he proteſteth that he will refuſe all maner of communion with them that deny him befor
<pb facs="tcp:7578:51"/>men. Thes words onleſe we be vtterlye void of all ſence ought vehemently to move our minds and ſo to fray vs / that for fear the hears of our heade ſhold ſtert vpp. But how ſo ever it be / onles we be ſo affected and moved as the great<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes of the mater and daunger requireth / ther remaineth nothi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g ells for vs but to look for hor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rible and moſt miſerable confuſion: wherin we may excuſe our fault ſo moche as we luſt / &amp; we may ſay that in this great frailtie and weaknes of nature / we rather ar worthye of mercy then of any ſeveritie and ſharpnes of puniſhment / it will not ſerve.
<note place="margin">Heb. xj.</note> For it is written on the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trarie part / that Moſes after he had ſene god by faith was ſo hardned and ſtrengthened / that no vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olence of te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptation co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>melt his mind / and be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d him from that great co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtancye. Wherfore whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we be ſo tendre and flexible that ther appear in vs no power of firme and conſtant minde / we ſignifie and declare plainlye that we be vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ignoraunt of god and his kingdome. Alſo whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we ar werned that we ought to be joyned &amp; cowpled w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> our head / we have gotten a good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly couler to exempt &amp; ſeparat our ſelves frome him / yf we ſay we ar me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> And were not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>i y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re befor vs men ſo well as we are? Yea yf we had nothinge ells / but even the bare doctrin of
<pb facs="tcp:7578:52" rendition="simple:additions"/>godlines / yet were al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> excuſes w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we can brig weack and of no value. But now ar we wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy more greater chek and condemnation / ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce we have ſo great &amp; notable exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ples / whos great authoritie ought vehemently to excite &amp; confirme our minds. Ther ar two chefe partes of this our exhortation or conſolation to be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſidered. The firſtis / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> this hath ben a commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſtate to the vniverſal bodye of the church alwai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>es and ever ſhalbe to the end of the world / that it was vexed with ſoche iniuries and contum<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> lies of the wicked / as it is reported in the Pſalme
<note place="margin">Pſalm. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.xxix.</note> / Thei have vexed me eve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> now fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> my iouth hether to / &amp; have drawn a plough ov<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:aber"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>er</ex>
               </expan> and ov<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:aber"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>er</ex>
               </expan> e veri ꝑt of my bak. The holy ghoſt in this place doth bri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g in the old church ſpeaki<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g on this wiſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it ſhold not ſeme now vnto vs a new y<hi rend="sup">i</hi>ng nor greavouſe / if we ſee in thes daies our cauſe &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dition to be like. S. Paul alſo reciti<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame place of an o y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>r Pſal. wher it is ſaid / We were as it were ſhepe led to the ſlaughter / doth de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> this ꝑtained not onli to one age / but it was &amp; ſhalbe the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / vſual &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinual ſtate of Chriſts church. So y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> if we ſee in this time y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church to be ſo ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dled &amp; vexed / bi y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> inſole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cie &amp; pride of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wicked / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſome bark at her / ſome bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te her / mani afflict her / &amp; alwaies inve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſome
<pb facs="tcp:7578:52"/>miſchef &amp; peſtile<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t deſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to her / yea &amp; ſet vp on her w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out ceaſig as it were mad dogges &amp; wil de raveni<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g beaſtes / let vs cal to reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhe was ſo vexed afflicted &amp; oppreſſed i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al times before. God doth geve vnto her ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>time / ſome reſt &amp; refreſhi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g &amp; as it were a time of true. And this is y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> w<hi rend="sup">c</hi> is ſpoken in the pſalme above alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d / y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> righteous lord doth cut i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſodre y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cordes of the wicked: &amp; i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> an other place / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he breaketh their rodde / 
<note place="margin">Pſal. c. xxv.</note> leſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> good being to moche preſſed ſhold fai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t &amp; move y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>ir ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des to i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>iquitie. But god wold alwaies have his church to be toſt in this world / &amp; as it were alwaies in a certai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>flict / reſervi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g for her quiet reſt in heven. The end of thes afflictions was alwaies bleſſed / yea truly god wrought this y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the church alwaies preſſed w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> mani &amp; great difficult calamities / was never vttrely oppreſſed.
<note place="margin">ij. Cor. iiij.</note> As it is ſaide in an other pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce / the wicked with all their labour did never optain y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thei deſiered. S. Paul alſo doth ſo glo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rye of like happye end &amp; iſſue of afflictions / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he ſheweth this grace of god to be ꝑpetuall in his church. We ſaith he / ar preſt with all kind of af<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>flictions / but we ar not killed w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſorow &amp; care / we live in greatnede &amp; pov<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:aber"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>er</ex>
               </expan>tie / iet ar we not for ſaken we are caſt down but we ꝑiſh not / alwai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>es carrie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g aboute the mortificatione of our lord
<pb facs="tcp:7578:53" rendition="simple:additions"/>Ieſus Chriſte / that his lyf alſo mai be declared in our mortal bodye. This iſſue and end / as we ſee that god hath alwaies made it happie and proſperouſe in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> perſequutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of the church / ought to bolden vs / ſeing we knowe that our fathers / who alſo acknowledged their frailty &amp; weaknes / had alwaies the victorie over their enemies / by cauſe thei continued conſtant in paciencye. I do entreat this firſt part of my ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortatione briefli / that j may come the ſoner to the ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d / which doth more pertaine to the pur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poſe. And that is / that we applie certaine exam<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ples of the martyres which were before vs / to our conſolation and confort. And in this kinde or nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bre ther be not two or thre / but a great &amp; thik cloude as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> apoſtle writeth to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Hebrues.
<note place="margin">Heb. xij.</note> Wherby he ſignifieth / that ther is ſo great a multitude of them / which hath ſuffred for the teſtimonie of the truth / that ſo well the aboun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>daunce of excellent examples / as the moſt gra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ve autoritie ought to provoke vs to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tentatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> patiencie / and moderation of minde. And leaſt my oration ſhold waxe to long in heaping vp together an i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>finite multitude of exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ples / j will o<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly ſpeak af y<hi rend="sup">s</hi> jewes / which ſuffered moſt gre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vouſe ꝑſequutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> true religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / both vndre y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tyra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nie of ki<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g Antiochꝰ / &amp; alſo ſhorthly after
<pb facs="tcp:7578:53"/>his death. We can not ſaie y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bre of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> afflicted me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was ſmal / whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a great mighty ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my as it were of martyrs was prepared to mai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>taine and defend y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> religion. Nether can we al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thei were certaine excellent prophets / who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> god had choſen forth and ſeparated frome y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> comon ſort of people / for ther were women / boyes / and infants / alſo in that nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bre of mar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyrs. Nether wil we ſay y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thei paſſed thorow y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ꝑſecution / only with ſome light loſſe / without great peril of lyfe / without great paines &amp; tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of bodies / ſeing / ther was no ki<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de of cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty vnproved in afflicti<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g / vexing / &amp; torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tig them. Let vs here alſo what y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> apoſtle doth ſaie of them / and doth ſet forth for vs to folow.</p>
            <p>Some ſaith he / 
<note place="margin">Heb. xj.</note> were hanged vp like belles and ſtretched / diſpiſing to be delivred y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thei might optaine a beter reſurrection: other were pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved with opprobrious wordes and ſtrippes / or with bondes and <expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abpri"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>pri</ex>
               </expan>ſonment: other wer ſtoned / or cutt inſondre / or killed with the ſwerd: o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſome went wandering hether and thether thorow hills &amp; caves of the earth. Let vs now come to make co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pariſon betwixt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; vs. Yf y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>i ſuffred ſo mani &amp; great torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> truth / w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> was as then but obſcure / what ought we to do in this great light / w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hath ſhined vnto vs in
<pb facs="tcp:7578:54"/>this time? God ſpeaketh vnto vs now as with full mouth. The greateſt gate of the kingdome of heven is made open vnto vs. Ieſus Chriſte comen fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> heven vnto vs doth ſo call vs to him / that we have him preſent as it were before our eies. In to how great ingratitude &amp; ſha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>full wic<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kednes ſhall we ru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>n i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to / if we have leſſ ſtomak &amp; love to bear &amp; ſuffre for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goſpel / the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thei had w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> did behold y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> promiſes of god but as it were a farre of / who had but a veray litle dore ope<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned to entre in to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> higdome of god / who had receaved only a reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>braunc &amp; obſcure teſtimoni in figures of Ieſus Chriſte? Thes great ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not be declared &amp; expreſſed w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> any wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des as thei beworthy. Wherfor j leave them to be weied in everie manes thoughts &amp; meditati<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ons. This doctrin as it hath a comon &amp; vniver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall reaſon / ſo it muſt be referred to the exerciſe &amp; ordre of everie manes lyfe. But everie man muſt apply it to his propre vſe &amp; profett apt for his own co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſolatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And j ſpeak this for this cau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe / leaſt y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thei w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſee them ſelves to be in no ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nifeſt perill / ſhold ſuppoſe this doctrin to be vai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne &amp; not to ꝑtaine to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Now thei arr not in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> handes of tira<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes / but what know thei howe god wil deal w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> herafter? Therfor we muſt be of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d &amp; judgme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> if any ꝑſequntio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we loked not for happe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto vs / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we fal not
<pb facs="tcp:7578:54"/>y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>r i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to vnwares &amp; vnꝓvided / but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we come to it prepared lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g befor ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, but j<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> feare y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>r be mani deaph eares to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">i</hi>s my oratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is made w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out fruit. For y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>i y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> live i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> quiet / havi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g all thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gs at wil / ar ſo far fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> prepari<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>m ſelves to take &amp; ſuffre death whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nede ſhal be / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>i have no ca<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re nor y<hi rend="sup">o</hi>ught of ſervi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g god at al. But y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>s ought to be al our ſtudie co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinualli / eſpetialli i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>s gre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>at troubleſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> times / wheri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we live i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> great peril In y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> time y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>i who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> god calleth to ſuffre for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> teſti<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>onie of his name / muſt y<hi rend="sup">i</hi>nke i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>verai dede y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thei were prepared lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g before / &amp; brought to this ſuffrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>c of evels / bi y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> motio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; certain jud<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>geme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>prit / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>i might bear y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>m ſelves y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>ri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> boldly &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tli. The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> alſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>i muſt dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly call to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>r reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>c al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> exhortatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>i have herd before / &amp; be ſo ſtirred vp w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> adv<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:aber"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>er</ex>
               </expan>tiſme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> valiau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſouldiare to take his armour whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he hereth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pet blowe. But what ſeke we?</p>
            <p>Truly in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>s perils we do nothi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g ells: but ſeke ſhiftes &amp; waies how to eſcape. I mea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſt ꝑt of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. For this ſame ꝑſequutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s is as it were a towche ſtone / wherw<hi rend="sup">t</hi> god doth trye &amp; ꝓve who be his: but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>r ar fewe fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> faith, cowrage &amp; godlines to wards god / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thei will offre the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelves fra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kly &amp; freely vnto death for his names ſake. This is a thing almoſt incredi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>i w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> do glory / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>i have ſome knowlege
<pb facs="tcp:7578:55"/>in the goſpell / arſo impudent and vnſhamfaſt / thei will vſe ſoch cavillations. Some will ſay / what ſhall it availl to confeſſ our faith before thos ſtubborne ſtifnecked men / which ar pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to warre agaiſt god him ſelfe? Is not this to caſt pearls before ſwine? As who wold ſay / Ieſus Chriſte doth not moſt plainly declare / y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> he doth requier of vs the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of his name / yea among moſt perverſe &amp; wicked men? But if this our teſtimonie do nothi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g profett to their e<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>difie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g / yet ſhal it profett to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>ir co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fuſion. Alwai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>es y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſion of our faith doth ſavour ſwetly before god although it bri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge death &amp; deſtructjo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to wicked men. Ther be other alſo which will ſay this / what ſhall our death profett when it ſhall ſeme to geve more offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce then vtilitie? As though god hath left to them ſelves fre choyſe to dye when thei will or when thei ſhall thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>k it the moſt apte time of death? But we co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trarie wiſe do obey him but as for the fruit y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> muſt co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me by our death / we leave to the hand &amp; provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of god. Wherfore the chriſtian man muſt moſt cheflye in what place ſo ever he be / dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly ſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he lyve in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſimplicitie &amp; integritie y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> god requireth / and y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he be not brought from y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> mi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d &amp; maner of godly &amp; holy life at any time w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> any dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gers or threatni<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gs. Let him eſchue ſo mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the
<pb facs="tcp:7578:55"/>as is poſſible the ragi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g madnes of the wol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ves / ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ſame w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>arenes be not joyned w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the prude<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce &amp; craftines of the fleſh. Firſt of all let him do this / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he geve over &amp; reſigne his lyfe in to the handes of god the moſt faithfull keaper. When he hath ordei<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ed &amp; kept dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly this ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ner &amp; faſhione of lyfe / yf afterward he fall in to the handes of enemies / let him thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>k &amp; perſwad him ſelfe / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he is brought in to y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> place of god / for this cauſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he mai have him a witnes of his ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne. Therfor ſei<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g he is called &amp; brought to y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>feſſion by the certaine decree of god / ther is no way to goo bak / onles he will be vnfaithful vn to him / to whom we have promiſed all our en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>devours both to lyve and dye: yea whos we arr although we had promiſed nothi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g at all. I mea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not herby to drive everie man of neceſſitie at all times to geve a full &amp; ꝑfect co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>ir faith / no not ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>times whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>i be aſked. For j know what meaſure &amp; moderatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> .ſ. Paul vſed / who was as readye w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hart &amp; mi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de to defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goſpel as any other. Nether was this ſpoken by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord Ieſus &amp; promiſed w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> out a cauſe / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> god wold ge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ve vs in y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> time &amp; matter / a mouth &amp; prude<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. As though he wold have ſaid / y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> office of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holie ghoſt / is not o<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>firme vs y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> we may be wil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>li<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g / bold &amp; ſtrong / but alſo it co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiſteth i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> gevi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g vs
<pb facs="tcp:7578:56" rendition="simple:additions"/>judgme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t prude<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e &amp; cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſail / how we mai / as it be cometh vs / governe &amp; rule our ſelves / in ſo gre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>at &amp; ſo herde amater. Truly this wholl treatiſe is to this e<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thei y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> be i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſoch diſtreſſes ſhold de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſier &amp; receav fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> heave<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> moderatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; prude<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce / not folowi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſail of the fleſhe to ſeke ſome ſhiftes to eſcape. But ther be y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> do obiect in this place / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the lord Ieſus yea whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he was aſked wold make to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> no a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſwer. But j ſat y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> this ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficeth not to take away y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> rule / w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he hath geve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to vs / to witnes our faith the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> when y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſion ther of is neceſſarily required. Furthermore / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he did nev<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:aber"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>er</ex>
               </expan> diſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ble or kepe ſile<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce for this purpo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe to ſave his life. Laſt of al y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he did neverma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke ſo doubtful a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> anſwer / but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teined a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> apt teſtimonie of that w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he had ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> before / or els did firſt ſatiffie the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> laye i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> waite to mark both his words &amp; dedes. Wherfor let al chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s be wel ꝑſwaded &amp; ſure of this thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ought more to eſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his life the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> teſtimonie of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> truth wherin god wil have y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> praiſe &amp; glorie of his na<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me to appear. Is it w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> out acauſe / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he calleth al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thos his witneſſes (for this doth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> word marti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re ſignifie) who ar brought to make anſwer be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore the enemies of faith and religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? Or is not this rather the cauſe / for y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he wold vſe all their ſpeaki<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g &amp; whole courſe of life to the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of his name? Wherin everie ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> muſt not ſo looke
<pb facs="tcp:7578:56"/>to his neghbour &amp; felowe / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he wil ſeme to do nothi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g at al w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> out his exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple &amp; teſtimonie. And this curioſitie is ſo much the mor to be eſchued becauſe we ar ꝓne to this vice of our owne na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. Peter whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he had herd of Chriſte that he ſhold be ledde i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his old age whether he wold not he e<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>quired what ſhold be come of Ioa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his felow &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panion. Ther is none of vs / w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> to avoide pe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rill &amp; dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger / wold not gladly make anſwer in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wiſe / by cauſe whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we ſhold ſuffre any thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g / by &amp; by this cometh in to our mi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de / what is the cauſe wher for j ſhold ſuffer more then others? But Ieſus Chriſte doth cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſail &amp; moniſh other wiſe vs al in como<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / &amp; everie ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> privatly / to be prepared &amp; readie / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> as he calleth on or other / ſo everie ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> come forth in his ordre. And j have ſhewed this before / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we ſhalbe vnarmed &amp; vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>prepared to take &amp; ſuffre martyrdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / o<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>leſſ we be fe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſed a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d armed w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the promiſes of god. Now re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineth to declare ple<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tifully ſoche ꝓmiſes / not y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we wil ſett forth everie one exactli / but to ſhe we the chefe &amp; moſt excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g / w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> god wold have vs to hope for / to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort vs i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our calamiti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>es. And ther be thre ſoche thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gs: the firſt / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſei<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>al the times both of our life &amp; death do co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiſt in his ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d / he wil ſo defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d vs bi his power / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> not one hear of our head ſhal faul but after his wil. Wherfor al faitful me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ought y<hi rend="sup">u</hi>s to beꝑſwaded / 
<pb facs="tcp:7578:57"/>in whos handes ſo ever thei be toſſed / that god in no wiſe wil lay a ſide that governaunce and cuſtodie / whiche he hath taken vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with ſo great care. Yf this perſwaſion of gods fatherly care / and prouidence did reſt and clea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ve depe in our harts / we ſhold be delivered out of hande / of the greateſt part of thes doubtes and difficulties / whiche do now trouble &amp; hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dre our dutye. We behold now the bitterneſſ of the tyraunts / and vnbridled crueltie / brawlig piviſhly in al ſharpnes of puniſments. And here by we judge that god hathe no more care / nor regard to defend and kepe vs in ſavetie.</p>
            <p>And therfor we be ſo ſtirred and provoked / by our own reaſons to looke and provide / for our ſelves / as though the whole hope of gods helpe and ſuccour were clean taken awaie. But on the other part / the ſo great providence of god / as he hath ſhewed vnto vs / ought to be vnto vs like a ſtronge fenced caſtle / which can be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver come<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with no power. Let vs therfor learn and hold faſt / this ſhort ſentence / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> our bodies ar in his hand and power / who alſo did creat them. And this is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cauſe / wherfor god hath de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>livered his / after a merveilouſe ſorte / and con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trarie the opinion and hope of al men / as Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drach / Miſach / and Abdenago / forth of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb facs="tcp:7578:57"/>oven / Daniel, out of the lions denne / pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter out of Herods priſon / wher in he was ſhot &amp; watched moſt diligently faſt bonnd in chaines. By thes examples he wold declare vnto vs / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he could ſtaye our enemies as it were with a certaine bridle / and that he had that power that when he wold / he could preſerve and as it were pluk vs out of the mouth of death it ſelf. Not that he doth alwaies thus deliver his fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſoch perils / but of right having the autoritie to apoint our lyfe and death / he will have vs perſuaded / that we are ſo continued and kept vndre his cuſtodie and tuition / that what ſo ev<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:aber"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>er</ex>
               </expan> the tyraunts do invent / or with what furie ſo ever thei ſet vpon vs / yet it is only in his hand to apoint lyfe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> death: and therfor this mater ought only to be refferred to his wil. But yf he ſuffre y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tyraunts to kil vs / yet our life is vnto him deare and moche more ſett by of him then it is worthie.
<note place="margin">Pſalm. c. xvj.</note> The which he did plainly declare to be ſo when he pronounced by the mouth of Dauid / that the death of his ſaints was honou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rable and preciouſe in his ſight.
<note place="margin">xxvj. cap.</note> And alſo when he ſaid by Eſay / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the earth it ſelfe ſhold ſhew forth the bloud that was ſhedd which ſemeth al to gether hidde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Now then lett the enemies of the goſpell be as bountiful and prodigall in
<pb facs="tcp:7578:58"/>ſhedding the martyrs bloud / as thei will / yet this muſt be / that thei ſhal make a reckening &amp; horrible accompt of the effuſion of that dear &amp; preciouſe bloud / yea even to the vttremoſt drop<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pe. But now / in this time thei do ſcornfully &amp; prowdly laugh / when thei burne the faithfull men / and after thei have dypte and waſhed the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelves in their bloud / thei be come ſo dronken / that thei care nothi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g at al / what murthers thei do. But yf we wil have this ſtay and modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of minde / that we can pacie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly abide / god wil at the laſt declare / that it was not without a cauſe that he ſo greatly eſtemed our life / and had it in ſo great honour. In the mean while let vs not take it to grefe / yf it be now beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to confirme and garniſh th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> goſpel / whiche excelleth heven and earth in worthines. And y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we may be mor ſurely perſwaded that god wil never leave vs as abiects in the hands of the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies / let vs not forget that ſame ſaing of Ie<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſus Chriſte / wherin he ſaith / that it is he him ſelfe whom men do perſequut in his membres.
<note place="margin">Act. ix.</note> God had ſaid before by Zacharye / who ſo tow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth youe towcheth the ſight of myn eie.
<note place="margin">Zach. ij.</note> This is moch more expreſſed / if we ſuffre for the goſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pel ſake / it is eve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as the ſonne of god hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelfe we<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re &amp; ſuffred in y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> afflictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Therfor let vs thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>k ſo
<pb facs="tcp:7578:58"/>y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Ieſꝰ Chriſte muſt forget hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelf / if he ſhold ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ve no care &amp; thought of vs at y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> time whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we be in priſon and dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger of life for his cauſe &amp; glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie: and let vs alſo knowe that god will take all the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tumelies and iniuries / as done agai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt his owne ſonne. Let vs come to the ſecond place of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſolatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is one of the greateſt among gods promiſes: that is / that god will ſo hold vs vpp w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the vertue of his ſpirit in thes afflictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s / that our enemies what ſo ever thei do / nor ſatan y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>ir chefe capitaine ſhall in any thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge go awai w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the over hand. And truly we do ſee how in that ne<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceſſitie / he doth ſhew the ſuccour and helpes of his grace. For the invi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cible ſtowtnes and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cye of mind w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is ſene in the true martyrs / is a notable token of that ſame moſt mighty power w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> god vſeth in his ſaints. Ther be two things in perſequutions grevous / tediouſe and intole<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rable to the fleſh wherof the one co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiſteth in the cheks and rebukes of men / the other in the pai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne and torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the bodie. In both thes kinds oftemtations god doth promiſe ſo his aſſiſtaun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce that we ſhall eaſely over come all the i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>famie and violence of the grefs and paine. And truly what he promiſeth he doth performe in dede w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> moſt manifeſt and aſſured helpe. Let vs then ta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke this bucklere to defend vs againſt all fear / 
<pb facs="tcp:7578:59"/>and let vs not meaſure the power of gods ſpirit ſo ſclendrely / that we ſhold not thinke and bele<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ve / that he will eaſely overcome all the iniuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es / bittrenes / and contumelies of menn. And of this divine and invincible operation / emong all other we have a notable exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple in this our age. A certain yonge man / who lived godlylye here w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> vs in this cytie / when he was taken at Dornick was co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demned with this ſentence / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> yfhe wold denye the confeſſion of his faith / he ſhold be but beheaded / but yfhe perſevered in his purpoſed opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / he ſhold be burned. Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he was aſked whether he wold do / he a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſwered plai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly / he who wil geve me this grace to dye pa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>patiently for his name / will alſo work by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fe ſame grace / that j may abide broyli<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g and bur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ning. We ought to take this ſentence not as pronounced of a mortall man / but of the holy ghoſt / that we ſhold thinke / that god can ſo wel confirme / and make vs over come al pains and torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts / as to move vs to take any other kinde of meaker death in good part. Yea we ſee alſo often times / what conſtancye he geveth to evel and wickedmen / who ſuffre for their evel dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des &amp; wickednes. I do not ſpeake of ſoch as be obſtinat &amp; hardned i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their wickednes w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> have no repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>taunce / but of them which do perceave con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſolation
<pb facs="tcp:7578:59"/>by the grace of Ieſus Chriſte / &amp; ſo do take and ſuffre quietly and with good wil moſt grevouſe and ſharpe paine: as we ſee a notable example in that thefe who turned at the death of our lord Ieſus Chriſte. Will god who aſſiſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teth with ſo great power wicked men y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſuffre condingly for their evell actes / forſake the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> who defend his cauſe / and will he not rather geve them invincible power? The third place of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes / whiche god promiſeth to his martyres / is the fruit which thei ought to look for of their ſufferi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g and of death it ſelfe / yfnede ſo requier. But this fruit is / that after thei have ſett forth and honoured gods name / &amp; edified his church with their teſtimonie / thei may be gathered to gether in immortal glorye with the lord Ieſus: But be cauſe we have ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> largely jnough be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore of this reward of eternall glorye / it is now ſufficient / to renue the memorie of thos things y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ar all readye ſpoken. Wherfor let the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full learn to reare vpp their head to the crown of immortall glorye / wher vnto god doth call them / let them not take the loſſe of this lyfe gre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vouſly / co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſideri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the greatnes / and worthines of the reward. And that thei may beſure and ꝑfectly perſwaded of this ſo great a good thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g / as can not be expreſſed with any ſpeache / nor in
<pb facs="tcp:7578:60"/>thought be comprehended / nor with any ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noure jnough eſtemed / lett them have continu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ally before their eies this like and conformable reaſon with our lord Ieſus Chriſte that in death it ſelfe thei behold lyfe / as he by ignominie of the croſſe and infamie came to gloriouſe reſurrectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / wherin all our felicitie / tri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vmph and joye con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſiſteth.</p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:7578:60"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
